Allocating objects

The recommended way to create an instance of a type T is to “call” T as if it were a function, with the arguments used to initialize the object. If T is a class and T has a matching constructor, then the arguments will used for constructor arguments:

(java.util.StringTokenizer "this/is/a/test" "/")

(You can think of the type T as being coerced to an instance-constructor function.)

If T is a container or collection type, then typically the arguments will be used to specify the child or component values. Many standard Scheme procedures fit this convention. For example in Kawa list and vector evaluate to types, rather than procedures as in standard Scheme, but because types can be used as constructor functions it just works:

(list 'a (+ 3 4) 'c) ⇒ (a 7 c)
(vector 'a 'b 'c) ⇒ #(a b c)

Any class T that has a default constructor and an add method can be initialized this way. Examples are java.util collection classes, and jawa.awt and javax.swing containers.

(java.util.ArrayList 11 22 33) ⇒ [11, 22, 333]

The above expression is equivalent to:

(let ((tmp (java.util.ArrayList)))
  (tmp:add 11)
  (tmp:add 22)
  (tmp:add 33)
  tmp)

Allocating Java arrays (see Creating-new-Java-arrays) uses a similar pattern:

(int[] 2 3 5 7 11)

Sometimes you want to set some named property to an initial value. You can do that using a keyword argument. For example:

(javax.swing.JButton text: "Do it!" tool-tip-text: "do it")

This is equivalent to using setter methods:

(let ((tmp (javax.swing.JButton)))
  (tmp:setText "Do it!")
  (tmp:setToolTipText "do it")
  tmp)

A keyword argument key-name: can can translated to either a setKeyName: or a addKeyName: method. The latter makes it convenient to add listeners:

(javax.swing.JButton
  text: "Do it!"
  action-listener:
   (object (java.awt.event.ActionListener)
     ((actionPerformed e) (do-the-action))))

This is equivalent to:

(let ((tmp (javax.swing.JButton)))
  (tmp:setText "Do it!")
  (tmp:addActionListener
    (object (java.awt.event.ActionListener)
      ((actionPerformed e) (do-the-action))))
  tmp)

Making use of so-called “SAM-conversion” (see SAM-conversion) makes it even more convenient:

(javax.swing.JButton
  text: "Do it!"
  action-listener:
   (lambda (e) (do-the-action)))

The general case allows for a mix of constructor arguments, property keywords, and child values:

class-type constructor-value... property-initializer... child-value...
constructor-value ::= expression
property-initializer ::= keyword expression
child-value ::= expression

First an object is constructed with the constructor-value arguments (if any) passed to the object constructor; then named properties (if any) are used to initialize named properties; and then remaining arguments are used to add child values.

There is an ambiguity if there is no property-initializer - we can’t distinguish between a constructor-value and a child-value. In that case, if there is a matching constructor method, then all of the arguments are constructor arguments; otherwise, there must a default constructor, and all of the arguments are child-value arguments.

There is a trick you can you if you need both constructor-value and child-value arguments: separate them with an “empty keyword” ||:. This matches a method named add, which means that the next argument effectively a child-value - as do all the remaining arguments. Example:

(let ((vec #(1 2 3)))
  (java.util.ArrayList vec ||: 4 5 6))
  ⇒ [1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6]

The compiler rewrites these allocations expression to generated efficient bytecode, assuming that the “function” being applied is a type known by the compiler. Most of the above expressions also work if the type is applied at run-time, in which case Kawa has to use slower reflection:

(define iarr int[])
(apply iarr (list 3 4 5)) ⇒ [3 4 5]

However addXxx methods and SAM-conversion are currently only recognized in the case of a class known at compile-time, not at run-time.

Here is a working Swing demo illustrating many of these techniques:

(import (class javax.swing
               JButton Box JFrame))
(define-simple-class HBox (Box)
  ((*init*) (invoke-special Box (this) '*init* 0)))

(define value 0)

(define txt
  (javax.swing.JLabel
   text: "0"))

(define (set-value i)
  (set! value i)
  (set! txt:text (number->string i)))

(define fr
  (JFrame
     title: "Hello!"
     (Box 1#|VERTICAL|# ||:
      (javax.swing.Box:createGlue)
      txt
      (javax.swing.Box:createGlue)
      (HBox
       (JButton ;; uses 1-argument constructor
	"Decrement" ;; constructor argument
	tool-tip-text: "decrement"
	action-listener: (lambda (e) (set-value (- value 1))))
       (javax.swing.Box:createGlue)
       (JButton ;; uses 0-argument constructor
	text: "Increment"
	tool-tip-text: "increment"
	action-listener: (lambda (e) (set-value (+ value 1))))))))
(fr:setSize 200 100)
(set! fr:visible #t)

If you prefer, you can use the older make special function:

Procedure: make type args ...

Constructs a new object instance of the specified type, which must be either a java.lang.Class or a <gnu.bytecode.ClassType>. Equivalent to:

type args ...

Another (semi-deprecated) function is to use the colon notation with the new pseudo-function. The following three are all equivalent:

(java.awt.Point:new x: 4 y: 3)
(make java.awt.Point: x: 4 y: 3)
(java.awt.Point x: 4 y: 3)

Up: Object, Classes and Modules

Previous: Calling Java methods from Scheme

Next: Accessing object fields

Android view construction

An Android user interface is constructed from View objects. The following is an example that illustrates some features of Kawa to help write views hierarchies, The example is self-contained, and can be built and run as described in Building for Android.

(require 'android-defs)
(activity hello
  (on-create-view 
   (define counter ::integer 0)
   (define counter-view
     (TextView text: "Not clicked yet."))
   (LinearLayout orientation: LinearLayout:VERTICAL
    (TextView text: "Hello, Android from Kawa Scheme!")
    (Button
     text: "Click here!"
     on-click-listener: (lambda (e)
                          (set! counter (+ counter 1))
                          (counter-view:setText
                           (format "Clicked ~d times." counter))))
    counter-view)))

The first import form imports various useful definitions from the Kawa Android library. Using these is not required for writing a Kawa application, but makes it more convenient.

The names LinearLayout, TextView, and Button are just aliases for standard Android View sub-classes. A few are prefined by (require 'android-defs), or you can define them yourself using define-alias.

An Android application consists of one or more activities, each of which is an instance of the android.app.Activity class. You can use the activity macro to define your Activity class. The first macro argument (in this case hello) is the class name, and the others are members of the class, in the syntax of a field-or-method-decl. The sub-form on-create-view is an abbreviation for declaring an onCreate method (which is called when the Activity starts up followed by a setContentView: The body of the on-create-view is evaluated. The result should be a View expression, which is passed to setContentView.

Procedure: current-activity [new-value]

With no arguments, returns the current Activity. If a new-value argument is given, sets the current activity. It is set automatically by the on-create and on-create-view methods of the activity macro.

Since current-activity is a parameter object, you can locally change the value using parameterize.

View object allocation

To create an instance of a View class you “call” the class as if it were a function, as described in Allocating objects. For example:

(TextView (this) text: "Hello, Android from Kawa Scheme!")

If you (require 'android-defs) that defines some special handling for View classes. You can leave out the (this) argument, which refers to the enclosing Activity:

(TextView text: "Hello, Android from Kawa Scheme!")

Event handlers

You can register event listeners on Android View objects using methods typically named setOnEVENTListener. For example setOnClickListener. When allocating an object you can leave out the set, and you can optionally use Scheme-style names: on-click-listener. The argument is an object of a special nested listener class, for example View$OnClickListener. These are single-method classes, so you can use a lambda expression and SAM-conversion will automatically create the needed listener class.

View object allocation
Event handlers

Up: Miscellaneous topics

Previous: Building for Android

Next: System inquiry

Programs and Bodies

Program units

A program-unit consists of a sequence of definitions and expressions.

program-unit ::= library-definition+ [statements]
  | statements
statements ::= statement+
statement ::= definition | expression | (begin statement* )

Typically a program-unit corresponds to a single source file (i.e.a named file in the file system). Evaluating a program-unit first requires the Kawa processor to analyze the whole program-unit to determine which names are defined by the definitions, and then evaluates each statement in order in the context of the defined names. The value of an expression is normally discarded, but may be printed out instead, depending on the evaluating context.

The read-eval-print-loop (REPL) reads one or more lines until it gets a valid program-unit, and evaluates it as above, except that the values of expressions are printed to the console (as if using the display function). Then the REPL reads and evaluates another program-unit, and so on. A definition in an earlier program-unit is remembered and is visible in a later program-unit unles it is overridden.

A comment in the first 2 lines of a source file may contain an encoding specification. This can be used to tell the reader what kind of character set encoding is used for the file. This only works for a character encoding that is compatible with ASCII (in the sense that if the high-order bit is clear then it’s an ASCII character), and that are no non-ASCI characters in the lines upto and including the encoding specification. A basic example is:

;; -*- coding: utf-8 -*-

In general any string that matches the following regular expression works:

coding[:=]\s*([-a-zA-Z0-9]+)

Libraries

A program-unit may contain library-definitions. In addition, any statements in program-unit comprise an implicit library, in that it can be given a name, and referenced from other libraries. Certain names defined in the program-unit can be exported, and then they can be imported by other libraries. For more information see Module classes.

It is recommended but not required that:

There should be at most one library-definition in a program-unit.

The library-name of the library-definition should match the name of the source file. For example:

(define-library (foo bar) ...)

should be in a file named foo/bar.scm.

If there is a library-definition, there should be no extra statements - i.e no implicit library definition. (It is disallowed to export any definitions from the implicit library if there is also a library-definition.)

Following these recommendations makes it easier to locate and organize libraries. However, having multiple libraries in a single program-unit is occasionally useful for source distribution and for testing.

Bodies

The body of a lambda, let, let*, let-values, let*-values, letrec, or letrec* expression, or that of a definition with a body consists of zero or more definitions or expressions followed by a final expression. (Standard Scheme requires that all definitions precede all expressions.)

body ::= statement*

Each identifier defined by a definition is local to the body. That is, the identifier is bound, and the region of the binding is the entire body. Example:

(let ((x 5))
  (define foo (lambda (y) (bar x y)))
  (define bar (lambda (a b) (+ (* a b) a)))
  (foo (+ x 3)))
⇒ 45

When begin, let-syntax, or letrec-syntax forms occur in a body prior to the first expression, they are spliced into the body. Some or all of the body, including portions wrapped in begin, let-syntax, or letrec-syntax forms, may be specified by a macro use.

An expanded body containing variable definitions can be converted into an equivalent letrec* expression. (If there is a definition following expressions you may need to convert the expressions to dummy definitions.) For example, the let expression in the above example is equivalent to

(let ((x 5))
  (letrec* ((foo (lambda (y) (bar x y)))
            (bar (lambda (a b) (+ (* a b) a))))
    (foo (+ x 3))))

Up: Syntax

Previous: Property access using colon notation

Next: Syntax and conditional compilation

Compiling to byte-code

All Scheme functions and source files are invisibly compiled into internal Java byte-codes. (A traditional interpreter is used for macro-expansion. Kawa used to also interpret “simple” expressions in interactive mode, but always compiling makes things more consistent, and allows for better stack traces on errors.)

To save speed when loading large Scheme source files, you probably want to pre-compile them and save them on your local disk. There are two ways to do this.

You can compile a Scheme source file to a single archive file. You do this using the compile-file function. The result is a single file that you can move around and load just like the .scm source file. You just specify the name of the archive file to the load procedure. Currently, the archive is a "zip" archive and has extension ".zip"; a future release will probably use "Java Archive" (jar) files. The advantage of compiling to an archive is that it is simple and transparent.

Alternatively, you can compile a Scheme source file to a collection of ‘.class’ files. You then use the standard Java class loading mechanism to load the code. The compiled class files do have to be installed somewhere in the CLASSPATH.

Compiling to a set of .class files

Invoking ‘kawa’ (or ‘java kawa.repl’) with the ‘-C’ flag will compile a ‘.scm’ source file into one or more ‘.class’ files:

kawa --main -C myprog.scm

You run it as follows:

kawa [-d outdirectory] [-P prefix] [-T topname] [--main | --applet | --servlet] -C infile ...

Note the ‘-C’ must come last, because ‘Kawa’ processes the arguments and options in order,

Here:

-C infile ...

The Scheme source files we want to compile.

-d outdirectory

The directory under which the resulting ‘.class’ files will be. The default is the current directory.

-P prefix

A string to prepend to the generated class names. The default is the empty string.

-T topname

The name of the "top" class - i.e. the one that contains the code for the top-level expressions and definitions. The default is generated from the infile and prefix.

--main

Generate a main method so that the resulting "top" class can be used as a stand-alone application. See Application compilation.

--applet

The resulting class inherits from java.applet.Applet, and can be used as an applet. See Applet compilation.

--servlet

The resulting class implements javax.servlet.http.HttpServlet, and can be used as a servlet in a servlet container like Tomcat.

When you actually want to load the classes, the outdirectory must be in your ‘CLASSPATH’. You can use the require syntax or the load function to load the code, by specifying the top-level class, either as a file name (relative to outdirectory) or as a class name. E.g. if you did:

kawa -d /usr/local/share/java -P my.lib. -T foo -C foosrc.scm

you can use either:

(require my.lib.foo)

or:

(load "my.lib.foo")

Using require is preferred as it imports the definitions from my.lib.foo into the compile-time environment, while load only imports the definitions into the run-time environment.

If you are compiling a Scheme source file (say ‘foosrc.scm’) that uses macros defined in some other file (say ‘macs.scm’), you need to make sure the definitions are visible to the compiler. One way to do that is with the ‘-f’:

kawa -f macs.scm -C foosrc.scm

Many of the options described earlier are relevant when compiling. Commonly used options include language selection, the --warn-xxx options, and --full-tailcalls.

Compiling to an archive file

Procedure: compile-file source-file compiled-archive

Compile the source-file, producing a .zip archive compiled-file.

For example, to byte-compile a file ‘foo.scm’ do:

(compile-file "foo.scm" "foo")

This will create ‘foo.zip’, which contains byte-compiled JVM .class files. You can move this file around, without worrying about class paths. To load the compiled file, you can later load the named file, as in either (load "foo") or (load "foo.zip"). This should have the same effect as loading ‘foo.scm’, except you will get the faster byte-compiled versions.

Compiling using Ant

Many Java projects use Ant for building Java projects. Kawa includes a <kawac> Ant task that simplifies compiling Kawa source files to classes. See the build.xml in the Kawa source distribution for examples. See the kawac task documentation for details.

Compiling to a standalone application

A Java application is a Java class with a special method (whose name is main). The application can be invoked directly by naming it in the Java command. If you want to generate an application from a Scheme program, create a Scheme source file with the definitions you need, plus the top-level actions that you want the application to execute.

For example, assuming your Scheme file is MyProgram.scm, you have two ways at your disposal to compile this Scheme program to a standalone application:

Compile in the regular way described in the previous section, but add the --main option.

kawa --main -C MyProgram.scm

The --main option will compile all Scheme programs received in arguments to standalone applications.

Compile in the regular way decribed in the previous section, but add the main: #t module compile option to your module.

;; MyProgram.scm
(module-name <myprogram>)
(module-compile-options main: #t)

kawa -C MyProgram.scm

This way you can compile multiple Scheme programs at once, and still control which one(s) will compile to standalone application(s).

Both methods will create a MyProgram.class which you can either load (as described in the previous section), or invoke as an application:

java MyProgram [args]

Your Scheme program can access the command-line arguments args by using the global variable ‘command-line-arguments’, or the R6RS function ‘command-line’.

If there is no explicit module-export in a module compiled with --main then no names are exported. (The default otherwise is for all names to be exported.)

Compiling to an applet

An applet is a Java class that inherits from java.applet.Applet. The applet can be downloaded and run in a Java-capable web-browser. To generate an applet from a Scheme program, write the Scheme program with appropriate definitions of the functions ‘init’, ‘start’, ‘stop’ and ‘destroy’. You must declare these as zero-argument functions with a <void> return-type.

Here is an example, based on the scribble applet in Flanagan’s "Java Examples in a Nutshell" (O’Reilly, 1997):

(define-private last-x 0)
(define-private last-y 0)

(define (init) :: void
  (let ((applet (this)))
    (applet:addMouseListener
     (object (java.awt.event.MouseAdapter)
	     ((mousePressed e)
	      (set! last-x (e:getX))
	      (set! last-y (e:getY)))))
    (applet:addMouseMotionListener
     (object (java.awt.event.MouseMotionAdapter)
	     ((mouseDragged e)
	      (let ((g (applet:getGraphics))
		    (x (e:getX))
		    (y (e:getY)))
		(g:drawLine last-x last-y x y)
		(set! last-x x)
		(set! last-y y)))))))

(define (start) :: void (format #t "called start.~%~!"))
(define (stop) :: void (format #t "called stop.~%~!"))
(define (destroy) :: void (format #t "called destroy.~%~!"))

You compile the program with the ‘--applet’ flag in addition to the normal ‘-C’ flag:

java kawa.repl --applet -C scribble.scm

You can then create a ‘.jar’ archive containing your applet:

jar cf scribble.jar scribble*.class

Finally, you create an ‘.html’ page referencing your applet and its support jars:

<html><head><title>Scribble testapp</title></head>
<body><h1>Scribble testapp</h1>
You can scribble here:
<br>
<applet code="scribble.class" archive="scribble.jar, kawa-2.92_invoke.jar" width=200 height=200>
Sorry, Java is needed.</applet>
</body></html>

The problem with using Kawa to write applets is that the Kawa .jar file is quite big, and may take a while to download over a network connection. Some possible solutions:

Try to strip out of the Kawa .jar any classes your applet doesn’t need.

Java 2 provides a mechanism to install a download extension.

Consider some alternative to applets, such as Java Web Start.

Compiling to a native executable

In the past it was possible to compile a Scheme program to native code using GCJ. However, using GCJ with Kawa is no longer supported, as GCJ is no longer being actively maintained.

Compiling to a set of .class files
Compiling to an archive file
Compiling using Ant
Compiling to a standalone application
Compiling to an applet
Compiling to a native executable

Up: How to start up and run Kawa

Previous: Exiting Kawa

Creating HTML nodes

The html prefix names a special namespace (see Namespaces) of functions to create HTML element nodes. For example, html:em is a constructor that when called creates a element node whose tag is em. If this element node is formatted as HTML, the result has an <em> tag.

Syntax: html:tag attributes ... content ...

Creates an element node whose tag is tag. The parameters are first zero or more attributes, followed by zero of more child values. An attribute is either an attribute value (possibly created using make-attribute), or a pair of arguments: A keyword followed by the attribute value. Child values are usually either strings (text content), or nested element nodes, but can also be comment or processing-instruction nodes.

(html:a href: "http://gnu.org/" "the "(html:i "GNU")" homepage")

The compound identifier html:tag is actually a type: When you call it as a function you’re using Kawa’s standard coercion of a type to its constructor function. This means you can do type tests:

(define some-node ...)
(if (instance? some-node html:blink)
  (error "blinking not allowed!"))

Object identity is currently not fully specified. Specifically, it is undefined if a nested (child) element node is copied “by value” or “by reference”. This is related to whether nodes have a parent reference. In the XPath/XQuery data model nodes do have a parent reference, and child nodes are conceptually copied. (In the actual implemention copying is commonly avoided.) Kawa/Scheme currently followed the XQuery copying semantics, which may not be the most appropriate for Scheme.

Up: Working with XML and HTML

Previous: Formatting XML

Next: Creating XML nodes

Creating New Record Types On-the-fly

Calling the make-record-type procedure creates a new record data type at run-time, without any compile-time support. It is primarily provided for compatibility; in most cases it is better to use the define-record-type form (see Record types).

Procedure: make-record-type type-name field-names

Returns a record-type descriptor, a value representing a new data type disjoint from all others. The type-name argument must be a string, but is only used for debugging purposes (such as the printed representation of a record of the new type). The field-names argument is a list of symbols naming the fields of a record of the new type. It is an error if the list contains any duplicates.

Procedure: record-constructor rtd [field-names]

Returns a procedure for constructing new members of the type represented by rtd. The returned procedure accepts exactly as many arguments as there are symbols in the given list, field-names; these are used, in order, as the initial values of those fields in a new record, which is returned by the constructor procedure. The values of any fields not named in that list are unspecified. The field-names argument defaults to the list of field names in the call to make-record-type that created the type represented by rtd; if the field-names argument is provided, it is an error if it contains any duplicates or any symbols not in the default list.

Procedure: record-predicate rtd

Returns a procedure for testing membership in the type represented by rtd. The returned procedure accepts exactly one argument and returns a true value if the argument is a member of the indicated record type; it returns a false value otherwise.

Procedure: record-accessor rtd field-name

Returns a procedure for reading the value of a particular field of a member of the type represented by rtd. The returned procedure accepts exactly one argument which must be a record of the appropriate type; it returns the current value of the field named by the symbol field-name in that record. The symbol field-name must be a member of the list of field-names in the call to make-record-type that created the type represented by rtd.

Procedure: record-modifier rtd field-name

Returns a procedure for writing the value of a particular field of a member of the type represented by rtd. The returned procedure accepts exactly two arguments: first, a record of the appropriate type, and second, an arbitrary Scheme value; it modifies the field named by the symbol field-name in that record to contain the given value. The returned value of the modifier procedure is unspecified. The symbol field-name must be a member of the list of field-names in the call to make-record-type that created the type represented by rtd.

Procedure: record? obj

Returns a true value if obj is a record of any type and a false value otherwise.

Procedure: record-type-descriptor record

Returns a record-type descriptor representing the type of the given record. That is, for example, if the returned descriptor were passed to record-predicate, the resulting predicate would return a true value when passed the given record.

Procedure: record-type-name rtd

Returns the type-name associated with the type represented by rtd. The returned value is eqv? to the type-name argument given in the call to make-record-type that created the type represented by rtd.

Procedure: record-type-field-names rtd

Returns a list of the symbols naming the fields in members of the type represented by rtd. The returned value is equal? to the field-names argument given in the call to make-record-type that created the type represented by rtd.

Records are extensions of the class Record. These procedures use the Java 1.1 reflection facility.

Up: Object, Classes and Modules

Previous: Record types

Next: Calling Java methods from Scheme

Exception handling

An exception is an object used to signal an error or other exceptional situation. The program or run-time system can throw the exception when an error is discovered. An exception handler is a program construct that registers an action to handle exceptions when the handler is active.

If an exception is thrown and not handled then the read-eval-print-loop will print a stack trace, and bring you back to the top level prompt. When not running interactively, an unhandled exception will normally cause Kawa to be exited.

In the Scheme exception model (as of R6RS and R7RS), exception handlers are one-argument procedures that determine the action the program takes when an exceptional situation is signaled. The system implicitly maintains a current exception handler in the dynamic environment. The program raises an exception by invoking the current exception handler, passing it an object encapsulating information about the exception. Any procedure accepting one argument can serve as an exception handler and any object can be used to represent an exception.

The Scheme exception model is implemented on top of the Java VM’s native exception model where the only objects that can be thrown are instances of java.lang.Throwable. Kawa also provides direct access to this native model, as well as older Scheme exception models.

Procedure: with-exception-handler handler thunk

It is an error if handler does not accept one argument. It is also an error if thunk does not accept zero arguments. The with-exception-handler procedure returns the results of invoking thunk. The handler is installed as the current exception handler in the dynamic environment used for the invocation of thunk.

(call-with-current-continuation
  (lambda (k)
   (with-exception-handler
    (lambda (x)
     (display "condition: ")
     (write x)
     (newline)
     (k 'exception))
    (lambda ()
     (+ 1 (raise ’an-error))))))
       ⇒ exception
       and prints condition: an-error

(with-exception-handler
 (lambda (x)
  (display "something went wrong\n"))
 (lambda ()
  (+ 1 (raise ’an-error))))
    prints something went wrong

After printing, the second example then raises another exception.

Performance note: The thunk is inlined if it is a lambda expression. However, the handler cannot be inlined even if it is a lambda expression, because it could be called by raise-continuable. Using the guard form is usually more efficient.

Procedure: raise obj

Raises an exception by invoking the current exception handler on obj. The handler is called with the same dynamic environment as that of the call to raise, except that the current exception handler is the one that was in place when the handler being called was installed. If the handler returns, then obj is re-raised in the same dynamic environment as the handler.

If obj is an instance of java.lang.Throwable, then raise has the same effect as primitive-throw.

Procedure: raise-continuable obj

Raises an exception by invoking the current exception handler on obj. The handler is called with the same dynamic environment as the call to raise-continuable, except that: (1) the current exception handler is the one that was in place when the handler being called was installed, and (2) if the handler being called returns, then it will again become the current exception handler. If the handler returns, the values it returns become the values returned by the call to raise-continuable.

(with-exception-handler
  (lambda (con)
    (cond
      ((string? con)
       (display con))
      (else
       (display "a warning has been issued")))
    42)
  (lambda ()
    (+ (raise-continuable "should be a number")
       23)))
      prints: should be a number
      ⇒ 65

Syntax: guard variable cond-clause+ body

The body is evaluated with an exception handler that binds the raised object to variable and, within the scope of that binding, evaluates the clauses as if they were the clauses of a cond expression. That implicit cond expression is evaluated with the continuation and dynamic environment of the guard expression. If every cond-clause’s test evaluates to #f and there is no else clause, then raise-continuable is invoked on the raised object within the dynamic environment of the original call to raise or raise-continuable, except that the current exception handler is that of the guard expression.

(guard (condition
         ((assq 'a condition) => cdr)
         ((assq 'b condition)))
  (raise (list (cons 'a 42))))
      ⇒ 42

(guard (condition
         ((assq 'a condition) => cdr)
         ((assq 'b condition)))
  (raise (list (cons 'b 23))))
      ⇒ (b . 23)

Performance note: Using guard is moderately efficient: there is some overhead compared to using native exception handling, but both the body and the handlers in the cond-clause are inlined.

Procedure: dynamic-wind in-guard thunk out-guard

All three arguments must be 0-argument procedures. First calls in-guard, then thunk, then out-guard. The result of the expression is that of thunk. If thunk is exited abnormally (by throwing an exception or invoking a continuation), out-guard is called.

If the continuation of the dynamic-wind is re-entered (which is not yet possible in Kawa), the in-guard is called again.

This function was added in R5RS.

Procedure: read-error? obj

Returns #t if obj is an object raised by the read procedure. (That is if obj is a gnu.text.SyntaxException.)

Procedure: file-error? obj

Returns #t if obj is an object raised by inability to open an input or output port on a file. (This includes java.io.FileNotFoundException as well as certain other exceptions.)

Simple error objects

Procedure: error message obj ...

Raises an exception as if by calling raise on a newly allocated simple error object, which encapsulates the information provided by message (which should a string), as well as any obj arguments, known as the irritants.

The string representation of a simple error object is as if calling (format "#<ERROR ~a~{ ~w~}>" message irritants). (That is the message is formatted as if with display while each irritant obj is formatted as if with write.)

This procedure is part of SRFI-23, and R7RS. It differs from (and is incompatible with) R6RS’s error procedure.

Procedure: error-object? obj

Returns #t if obj is a simple error object. Specifically, that obj is an instance of kawa.lang.NamedException. Otherwise, it returns #f.

Procedure: error-object-message error-object

Returns the message encapsulated by error-object, which must be a simple error object.

Procedure: error-object-irritants error-object

Returns a list of the irritants (other arguments) encapsulated by error-object, which must be a simple error object.

Named exceptions

These functions associate a symbol with exceptions and handlers: A handler catches an exception if the symbol matches.

Procedure: catch key thunk handler

Invoke thunk in the dynamic context of handler for exceptions matching key. If thunk throws to the symbol key, then handler is invoked this way:

(handler key args ...)

key may be a symbol. The thunk takes no arguments. If thunk returns normally, that is the return value of catch.

Handler is invoked outside the scope of its own catch. If handler again throws to the same key, a new handler from further up the call chain is invoked.

If the key is #t, then a throw to any symbol will match this call to catch.

Procedure: throw key arg ...

Invoke the catch form matching key, passing the args to the current handler.

If the key is a symbol it will match catches of the same symbol or of #t.

If there is no handler at all, an error is signaled.

Native exception handling

Procedure: primitive-throw exception

Throws the exception, which must be an instance of a sub-class of java.lang.Throwable.

Syntax: try-finally body handler

Evaluate body, and return its result. However, before it returns, evaluate handler. Even if body returns abnormally (by throwing an exception), handler is evaluated.

(This is implemented just like Java’s try-finally. However, the current implementation does not duplicate the handler.)

Syntax: try-catch body handler ...

Evaluate body, in the context of the given handler specifications. Each handler has the form:

var type exp ...

If an exception is thrown in body, the first handler is selected such that the thrown exception is an instance of the handler’s type. If no handler is selected, the exception is propagated through the dynamic execution context until a matching handler is found. (If no matching handler is found, then an error message is printed, and the computation terminated.)

Once a handler is selected, the var is bound to the thrown exception, and the exp in the handler are executed. The result of the try-catch is the result of body if no exception is thrown, or the value of the last exp in the selected handler if an exception is thrown.

(This is implemented just like Java’s try-catch.)

Simple error objects
Named exceptions
Native exception handling

Up: Program structure

Previous: Threads

Lazy evaluation

Lazy evaluation (or call-by-need) delays evaluating an expression until it is actually needed; when it is evaluated, the result is saved so repeated evaluation is not needed. Lazy evaluation is a technique that can make some algorithms easier to express compactly or much more efficiently, or both. It is the normal evaluation mechanism for strict functional (side-effect-free) languages such as Haskell. However, automatic lazy evaluation is awkward to combine with side-effects such as input-output. It can also be difficult to implement lazy evaluation efficiently, as it requires more book-keeping.

Kawa, like other Schemes, uses “eager evaluation” - an expression is normally evaluated immediately, unless it is wrapped in a special form. Standard Scheme has some basic building blocks for “manual” lazy evaluation, using an explicit delay operator to indicate that an expression is to be evaluated lazily, yielding a promise, and a force function to force evaluation of a promise. This functionality is enhanced in SRFI 45, in R7RS-draft (based on SRFI 45), and SRFI 41 (lazy lists aka streams).

Kawa makes lazy evaluation easier to use, by implicit forcing: The promise is automatically evaluated (forced) when used in a context that requires a normal value, such as arithmetic needing a number. Kawa enhances lazy evaluation in other ways, including support for safe multi-threaded programming.

Delayed evaluation

Syntax: delay expression

The delay construct is used together with the procedure force to implement lazy evaluation or call by need.

The result of (delay expression) is a promise which at some point in the future may be asked (by the force procedure) to evaluate expression, and deliver the resulting value. The effect of expression returning multiple values is unspecified.

Syntax: delay-force expression

Syntax: lazy expression

The delay-force construct is similar to delay, but it is expected that its argument evaluates to a promise. (Kawa treats a non-promise value as if it were a forced promise.) The returned promise, when forced, will evaluate to whatever the original promise would have evaluated to if it had been forced.

The expression (delay-force expression) is conceptually similar to (delay (force expression)), with the difference that forcing the result of delay-force will in effect result in a tail call to (force expression), while forcing the result of (delay (force expression)) might not. Thus iterative lazy algorithms that might result in a long series of chains of delay and force can be rewritten using delay-force to prevent consuming unbounded space during evaluation.

Using delay-force or lazy is equivalent. The name delay-force is from R7RS; the name lazy is from the older SRFI-45.

Procedure: eager obj

Returns a promise that when forced will return obj. It is similar to delay, but does not delay its argument; it is a procedure rather than syntax.

The Kawa implementation just returns obj as-is. This is because Kawa treats as equivalent a value and forced promise evaluating to the value.

Procedure: force promise

The force procedure forces the value of promise. As a Kawa extension, if the promise is not a promise (a value that does not implement gnu.mapping.Lazy) then the argument is returned unchanged. If no value has been computed for the promise, then a value is computed and returned. The value of the promise is cached (or “memoized”) so that if it is forced a second time, the previously computed value is returned.

(force (delay (+ 1 2)))                ⇒  3

(let ((p (delay (+ 1 2))))
  (list (force p) (force p)))          ⇒  (3 3)

(define integers
  (letrec ((next
            (lambda (n)
              (cons n (delay (next (+ n 1)))))))
    (next 0)))
(define head 
  (lambda (stream) (car (force stream)))) 
(define tail 
  (lambda (stream) (cdr (force stream)))) 

(head (tail (tail integers)))          ⇒  2

The following example is a mechanical transformation of a lazy stream-filtering algorithm into Scheme. Each call to a constructor is wrapped in delay, and each argument passed to a deconstructor is wrapped in force. The use of (lazy ...) instead of (delay (force ...)) around the body of the procedure ensures that an ever-growing sequence of pending promises does not exhaust the heap.

(define (stream-filter p? s)
  (lazy
   (if (null? (force s))
       (delay ’())
       (let ((h (car (force s)))
             (t (cdr (force s))))
         (if (p? h)
             (delay (cons h (stream-filter p? t)))
             (stream-filter p? t))))))

(head (tail (tail (stream-filter odd? integers))))
    ⇒ 5

Procedure: force* promise

Does force as many times as necessary to produce a non-promise. (A non-promise is a value that does not implement gnu.mapping.Lazy, or if it does implement gnu.mapping.Lazy then forcing the value using the getValue method yields the receiver.)

The force* function is a Kawa extension. Kawa will add implicit calls to force* in most contexts that need it, but you can also call it explicitly.

The following examples are not intended to illustrate good programming style, as delay, lazy, and force are mainly intended for programs written in the functional style. However, they do illustrate the property that only one value is computed for a promise, no matter how many times it is forced.

(define count 0)
(define p
  (delay (begin (set! count (+ count 1))
                (if (> count x)
                    count
                    (force p)))))
(define x 5)
p                  ⇒ a promise
(force p)          ⇒ 6
p                  ⇒ a promise, still
(begin (set! x 10)
       (force p))  ⇒ 6

Implicit forcing

If you pass a promise as an argument to a function like sqrt if must first be forced to a number. In general, Kawa does this automatically (implicitly) as needed, depending on the context. For example:

(+ (delay (* 3 7)) 13)   ⇒ 34

Other functions, like cons have no problems with promises, and automatic forcing would be undesirable.

Generally, implicit forcing happens for arguments that require a specific type, and does not happen for arguments that work on any type (or Object).

Implicit forcing happens for:

arguments to arithmetic functions;

the sequence and the index in indexing operations, like string-ref;

the operands to eqv? and equal? are forced, though the operands to eq? are not;

port operands to port functions;

the value to be emitted by a display but not the value to be emitted by a write;

the function in an application.

Type membership tests, such as the instance? operation, generally do not force their values.

The exact behavior for when implicit forcing happens is a work-in-progress: There are certainly places where implicit forcing doesn’t happen while it should; there are also likely to be places where implicit forcing happens while it is undesirable.

Most Scheme implementations are such that a forced promise behaves differently from its forced value, but some Scheme implementions are such that there is no means by which a promise can be operationally distinguished from its forced value. Kawa is a hybrid: Kawa tries to minimize the difference between a forced promise and its forced value, and may freely optimize and replace a forced promise with its value.

Blank promises

A blank promise is a promise that doesn’t (yet) have a value or a rule for calculating the value. Forcing a blank promise will wait forever, until some other thread makes the promise non-blank.

Blank promises are useful as a synchronization mechanism - you can use it to safely pass data from one thread (the producer) to another thread (the consumer). Note that you can only pass one value for a given promise: To pass multiple values, you need multiple promises.

(define p (promise))
(future ;; Consumer thread
  (begin
    (do-stuff)
    (define v (force promise)) ; waits until promise-set-value!
    (do-stuff-with v)))
;; Producer thread
... do stuff ...
(promise-set-value! p (calculate-value))

Constructor: promise

Calling promise as a zero-argument constructor creates a new blank promise.

This calls the constructor for gnu.mapping.Promise. You can also create a non-blank promise, by setting one of the value, alias, thunk, or exception properties. Doing so is equivalent to calling promise-set-value!, promise-set-alias!, promise-set-thunk!, or promise-set-exception! on the resulting promise. For example: (delay exp) is equivalent to:

(promise thunk: (lambda() exp))

The following four procedures require that their first arguments be blank promises. When the procedure returns, the promise is no longer blank, and cannot be changed. This is because a promise is conceptually a placeholder for a single “not-yet-known” value; it is not a location that can be assigned multiple times. The former enables clean and safe (“declarative") use of multiple threads; the latter is much trickier.

Procedure: promise-set-value! promise value

Sets the value of the promise to value, which makes the promise forced.

Procedure: promise-set-exception! promise exception

Associate exception with the promise. When the promise is forced the exception gets thrown.

Procedure: promise-set-alias! promise other

Bind the promise to be an alias of other. Forcing promise will cause other to be forced.

Procedure: promise-set-thunk! promise thunk

Associate thunk (a zero-argument procedure) with the promise. The first time the promise is forced will causes the thunk to be called, with the result (a value or an exception) saved for future calls.

Procedure: make-promise obj

The make-promise procedure returns a promise which, when forced, will return obj. It is similar to delay, but does not delay its argument: it is a procedure rather than syntax. If obj is already a promise, it is returned.

Because of Kawa’s implicit forcing, there is seldom a need to use make-promise, except for portability.

Lazy and eager types

Type: promise[T]

This parameterized type is the type of promises that evaluate to an value of type T. It is equivalent to the Java interface gnu.mapping.Lazy<T>. The implementation class for promises is usually gnu.mapping.Promise, though there are other classes that implement Lazy, most notably gnu.mapping.Future, used for futures, which are promises evaluated in a separate thread.

Note the distinction between the types integer (the type of actual (eager) integer values), and promise[integer] (the type of (lazy) promises that evaluate to integer). The two are compatible: if a promise[integer] value is provided in a context requiring an integer then it is automatically evaluated (forced). If an integer value is provided in context requiring a promise[integer], that conversion is basically a no-op (though the compiler may wrap the integer in a pre-forced promise).

In a fully-lazy language there would be no distinction, or at least the promise type would be the default. However, Kawa is a mostly-eager language, so the eager type is the default. This makes efficient code-generation easier: If an expression has an eager type, then the compiler can generate code that works on its values directly, without having to check for laziness.

Delayed evaluation
Implicit forcing
Blank promises
Lazy and eager types

Up: Program structure

Previous: Local binding constructs

Next: Threads

Lexical and datum syntax

The syntax of Scheme code is organized in three levels:

the lexical syntax that describes how a program text is split into a sequence of lexemes,

the datum syntax, formulated in terms of the lexical syntax, that structures the lexeme sequence as a sequence of syntactic data, where a syntactic datum is a recursively structured entity,

the program syntax formulated in terms of the datum syntax, imposing further structure and assigning meaning to syntactic data.

Syntactic data (also called external representations) double as a notation for objects, and the read and write procedures can be used for reading and writing syntactic data, converting between their textual representation and the corresponding objects. Each syntactic datum represents a corresponding datum value. A syntactic datum can be used in a program to obtain the corresponding datum value using quote.

Scheme source code consists of syntactic data and (non–significant) comments. Syntactic data in Scheme source code are called forms. (A form nested inside another form is called a subform.) Consequently, Scheme’s syntax has the property that any sequence of characters that is a form is also a syntactic datum representing some object. This can lead to confusion, since it may not be obvious out of context whether a given sequence of characters is intended to be a representation of objects or the text of a program. It is also a source of power, since it facilitates writing programs such as interpreters or compilers that treat programs as objects (or vice versa).

A datum value may have several different external representations. For example, both #e28.000 and #x1c are syntactic data representing the exact integer object 28, and the syntactic data (8 13), ( 08 13 ), (8 . (13 . ())) all represent a list containing the exact integer objects 8 and 13. Syntactic data that represent equal objects (in the sense of equal?) are always equivalent as forms of a program.

Because of the close correspondence between syntactic data and datum values, we sometimes uses the term datum for either a syntactic datum or a datum value when the exact meaning is apparent from the context.

Up: Syntax

Previous: Notation

Next: Lexical syntax

Named output formats

The --output-format (or --format) command-line switch can be used to override the default format for how values are printed on the standard output. This format is used for values printed by the read-eval-print interactive interface. It is also used to control how values are printed when Kawa evaluates a file named on the command line (using the -f flag or just a script name). (It also affects applications compiled with the --main flag.) It currently affects how values are printed by a load, though that may change.

The default format depends on the current programming language. For Scheme, the default is scheme for read-eval-print interaction, and ignore for files that are loaded.

The formats currently supported include the following:

scheme

Values are printed in a format matching the Scheme programming language, as if using display. "Groups" or "elements" are written as lists.

readable-scheme

Like scheme, as if using write: Values are generally printed in a way that they can be read back by a Scheme reader. For example, strings have quotation marks, and character values are written like ‘#\A’.

elisp

Values are printed in a format matching the Emacs Lisp programming language. Mostly the same as scheme.

readable-elisp

Like elisp, but values are generally printed in a way that they can be read back by an Emacs Lisp reader. For example, strings have quotation marks, and character values are written like ‘?A’.

clisp
commonlisp

Values are printed in a format matching the Common Lisp programming language, as if written by princ. Mostly the same as scheme.

readable-clisp
readable-commonlisp

Like clisp, but as if written by prin1: values are generally printed in a way that they can be read back by a Common Lisp reader. For example, strings have quotation marks, and character values are written like ‘#\A’.

xml
xhtml
html

Values are printed in XML, XHTML, or HTML format. This is discussed in more detail in Formatting XML.

cgi

The output should follow the CGI standards. I.e. assume that this script is invoked by a web server as a CGI script/program, and that the output should start with some response header, followed by the actual response data. To generate the response headers, use the response-header function. If the Content-type response header has not been specified, and it is required by the CGI standard, Kawa will attempt to infer an appropriate Content-type depending on the following value.

ignore

Top-level values are ignored, instead of printed.

Up: Input, output, and file handling

Next: Paths - file name, URLs, and URIs

News - Recent Changes

These changes are in more-or-less reverse chronological order, with the most recent changes first.

See also the list of Qexo (XQuery)-specific changes.

In Git repository (invoke branch) since last release

Most places where you could declare a new identifier binding have been generalized to accept patterns, including literals and boolean guards.

The new form match form is a generalization of case using patterns.

The internal calling convention used for “apply” (ie. calling an unknown-at-compile-time procedure) has been completely changed.

Major changes to strings:

Incompatible change: String literals are now gnu.lists.IString rather than java.lang.String. The advantage of using gnu.lists.IString is that string-ref and string-length are (roughly) constant-time, rather than having to linearly scan the string.

Incompatible change: The procedures string-append, string-map, substring, list->string, vector->string, string-downcase, string-upcase, string-foldcase, string-titlecase, and the constructor string return an immutable string (an IString). (The function string-copy is similar to substring, but returns a mutable string.) This is a work-in-progress with the goal of implementing SRFI-140: Other procedures will be changed to return immutable strings.

If you (import (scheme base)) standard procedures such as string-append will return mutable strings; if you (import (kawa base)) the procedures will return immutable strings. The command-line options --r5rs or --r6rs or --r7rs override the default so these procedures return mutable strings.

Incompatible change: Treating a string as a sequence is now simpler but possibly slower: The I’th element is now the I’th Unicode code point. Indexing with function-call syntax (string i) is the same as (string-ref string i) and (length string) is the same as (string-length string). This applies to all classes that implement java.lang.CharSequence. Indexing may be a linear-time operation (thus much slower), unless the string is an IString (in which case it is constant-time),

Incompatible change: Before, if a Java parameter type was java.lang.String Kawa would accept any value, converting it using Object’s toString method. Now Kawa will reject an argument if it is not a java.lang.CharSequence.

New procedures: istring?, reverse-list->string, string-any, string-concatenate, string-concatenate-reverse, string-contains, string-contains-right, string-count, string-drop, string-drop-right, string-every, string-filter, string-fold, string-fold-right, string-for-each-index, string-index, string-index-right, string-join, string-map-index, string-null?, string-prefix?, string-prefix-length, string-repeat, string-remove, string-replace, string-skip, string-skip-right, string-split, string-suffix?, string-suffix-length, string-tabulate, string-take, string-take-right, string-trim, string-trim-right, string-trim-both, string-unfold, string-unfold-right, string->utf16, string->utf16be, string->utf16le, utf16->string, utf16be->string, utf16le->string, xsubstring. These follow SRFI-140 and return immutable strings. (Some of these had previously been available in SRFI-13, but the older versions return mutable strings.)

Incompatible change: Kawa traditionally followed Java in allowing you to pass an array with the “rest” arguments to a varargs method. For example, you could write:

(define args (Object[] 3 "cm"))
(java.lang.String:format "length:%s%s" args)

This is no longer allowed. Instead, use the splice operator:

(java.lang.String:format "length:%s%s" @args)

Incompatible change: You used to be able to write a type-specifier in a formal parameter or return type without using ‘::’, as in:

(define (incr (x int)) int (+ x 1))

This is no longer allowed, because it conflicts with the syntax for patterns. Instead you have to write:

(define (incr (x ::int)) ::int (+ x 1))

New type aliases bitvector and c16vector. The latter is a uniform vector type for wrapping char[] arrays.

You can convert a Java array (for example a int[] to the corresponing uniform vector type (for example u32vector) using the as pseudo-function or the corresponding conversion procedure (for example ->u32vector). The result shares storage with the array, so changes in one will update the other.

The expression (module-class) evaluates to the containing module class.

Change the mangling for field and local variables names to match the Symbolic Freedom style.

Kawa 2.3 (January 13, 2017)

Moved Kawa’s source code repository (version control system) to use git, hosted at GitLab.

Issues (bugs, feature requests, etc) should now be reported using the GitLab Issue Tracker.

New with-docbook-stylesheets to make it easier to build the documentation with better functionality and look.

The command-line option console:jline-mouse=yes enables moving the input cursor using a mouse click, when using JLine in the REPL on common xterm-like terminals. This is disabled by default because it conflicts with other mouse actions, such as making a selection for copying text. You can press shift to get the terminal’s standard mouse handling.

Kawa 2.2 (November 12, 2016)

A binary release is no longer just a Kawa .jar file, but is now a zip archive that also includes shell/batch scripts for running Kawa, useful third-party libraries, and the complete documentation in EPUB format. The archives are named kawa-version.zip.

The kawa --browse-manual switch makes it easy to browse the local documentation.

The (kawa pictures) library lets you create “picture” objects, display them, transform them, combine them, and more.

There is a new API for pretty-printing.

Basic support for Java 9 (though still some issues).

Generated files like Makefile.in and configure are no longer in the Subversion source code repository, though they are still included in the distributed kawa-version.tar.gz releases. The new top-level script autogen.sh should be run before configure.

Kawa traditionally followed Java in allowing you to pass an array with the "rest" arguments to a varargs method. (A "varargs" method includes Java varargs methods, as well as Kawa methods with a #!rest parameter that is explicitly typed to be an array type.) For example, you could write:

(define args (Object[] 3 "cm"))
(java.lang.String:format "length:%s%s" args)

This is deprecated, and may stop working in a future release. Instead, use the splice operator:

(java.lang.String:format "length:%s%s" @args)

More options for range objects. For example, you can write [1 by: 2 <=: 9].

Many enhancements to arrays and vectors:

Shape specifiers (used when creating an array) can now be one of a rank-2 array of low/high-bounds, as in SRFI-25; a vector of upper bounds; or a vector of ranges.

New type specifiers for array: array is any array (i.e. any gnu.lists.Array); arrayN is the same restricted to rank N; array[etype] or arrayN[etype] restrict the types of elements to etype.

If the etype is a primitive type (for example array2[double]) then indexing is optimized to method calls that avoid object allocation.

Generalized array indexing: If A is an array (or a vector), then the expression: (A I J K ...) in general evaluates to an array B such that: (B i1 i2 ... j1 j2 ... k1 k2 ... ...) is (A (I i1 i2 ..) (J j1 j2 ...) (K k1 k2 ...) ...)

If an index I is an integer, it is treated as a zero-index array - a scalar.

For example: if (define B (A 2 [4 <: 10])) then (B i) is (A 2 (+ i 4)).

The procedure array-index-ref is does the above indexing explicitly: (array-index-ref A I J K ...) is (A I J K ...). The result is a read-only snapshot.

The procedure array-index-share is like array-index-ref but creates a modifiable view into argument array.

(build-array shape procedure) is a general constructor for lazy arrays: If A is the result, then (A i j k ...) is (procedure [I J K ...]).

array-transform creates a view, with a mapping of the indexes.

Other new procedures (like those in the Racket math package): array-size, array-fill!, array-copy!, array-transform, array-reshape, array-flatten, array->vector, index-array, build-array.

Add Common Lisp array reader syntax (#rankA) with Guile extensions, including reader sypport for multi-dimensional uniform (primitive) arrays. This is also used when printing arrays.

New format-array procedure print an array a tabular 2-dimensional (APL-like) format. This format is used by default in the top-level of the REPL.

Print bit-vectors using the Common Lisp (and Guile) reader syntax. For example #*1100110. Enhanced the reader to read this format.

Various REPL enhancements and new features:

The -w switch to create a new REPL window can be followed by various sub-options to control how and where the window is created. For example -wbrowser creates a new window using your default web browser.

Prompts are now normally specified using printf-style templates. The normal prompt template is specified by the input-prompt1 variable, while continuation lines use input-prompt2. These can be initialized by command-line options console:prompt1 and console:prompt2, or otherwise use language-specific defaults. You can still use set-input-port-prompter! to set a more general prompt-procedure, but it is now only called for the initial line of a command, not continuation lines.

The new --with-jline3 configure option builds support for the JLine (version 3) library for handling console input, similar to GNU readline.

Context-dependent command-completion (tab-completion) works when using JLine.

Various REPL enhancements when using DomTerm.

If you “print” an XML/HTML node, it gets inserted into the DomTerm objects. You print images, tables, fancy text, and more.

If you “print” a picture object or a BuferredImage the picture is shown in the DomTerm console.

You can load or modify styles with the domterm-load-stylesheet procedure.

When pretty-printing, calculation of line-breaks and indentation is handled by DomTerm. If you change the window width, DomTerm will dynamically re-calculate the line-breaks of previous pretten output. This works even in the case of a session saved to an HTML file, as long as JavaScript is enabled.

Hide/show buttons are emitted as part of the default prompt.

Multiple literals that have the same value (as in equal?) get compiled to the same object.

The syntax &<[expr] is now equivalent to &<{&[expr]}, assuming expr is an expression that evaluates to a string that named an existing file. That file is read is the result is the contents of the file (as if by (path-data expr)).

Kawa 2.1 (October 26, 2015)

Lots of little changes, and some big changes to sequences and strings.

Enhancements to the Kawa tutorial.

Added parameter as a new typename, for Scheme parameter objects. It can be parameterized (for example parameter[string]) for better type inference when "calling" (reading) the parameter.

We now define “interactive mode” as a REPL or a source module that uses the default global top-level environment or a source module imported/required by a interactive module. Interactive mode attempts to support dynamic re-definition and re-loading of function and other definitions. This is a work-in-progres; interactive mode currently uses extra indirection to support re-definitions (at a slight performance cost).

Various changes and fixes in Path/URI handling. Most significantly, the resolve argorithm used by resolve-uri was re-written to use the algorithm from RFC-3986, rather than the obsolete RFC-2396 algorithm used by java.net.URI.resolve.

Change to mangle class and package name in Symbolic Freedom style. This means that class names and class filenames usually match the source file, even if special charaters are used, except for a small number of disallowed characters. Note this is currently only used for class and package names.

Allow 'synchronized and 'strictfp as access flags for methods.

You can now have a type-specifier for define-variable.

Better support for forward references between macros.

Added unsigned primitive integer types ubyte, ushort, uint, and ulong. These are represented at run-time by the corresponding signed types, but Kawa generates code to do unsigned arithmethic and comparisons. Corresponding boxed classes are gnu.math.UByte, gnu.math.UShort, gnu.math.UInt, and gnu.math.ULong.

Improvements and unification of sequences and strings:

The new sequence type generalizes lists, vectors, arrays, strings, and more. It is implemented as the java.util.List interface, but strings (java.lang.CharSequence) and Java arrays are compatible with sequence and converted as needed.

The length function is generalized to arbitrary sequences. (For strings it uses the CharSequence.length method, which returns the number of (16-bit) code units. This is different from the string-length function, which returns the number of Unicode code points.)

A new pseudo-character value #\ignorable-char is introduced. It is ignored in string-construction contexts.

The function-call syntax for indexing works for all sequences. If the sequence is a string, the result is the Unicode (20-bit) scalar value at the specified index. If index references the trailing surrogate of a surrogate pair the result is #\ignorable-char. This allows efficient indexing of strings: Handing of surrogate pairs are handled automatically as long as #\ignorable-char is skipped.

Indexing of uniform vector types (such as s64vector or f64vector or u16vector) now return the “standard” primitive type (such as long or double) or the new unsigned primitive (such as ushort). This improves performance (since we can generally use primitive types), and improves compatibility with Java arrays. Specifically, s64vector now implements Sequence<Long>, and thus java.util.List<Long> Note that indexing a f64vector returns a double which as an object is a java.lang.Double, not the Kawa floating-point type gnu.math.DFloNum. The result is usually the same, but eqv? might return a different result than previously.

The arguments to map, for-each, and vector-for-each can now be any sequence (including strings and native arrays). The arguments to vector-for-each can now be arbitrary java.util.List values. All of these are inlined. If the sequence type is known, more efficient custom code is generated.

A range represents an enumerable sequence, normally integers, but it is represented compactly using the start value, the step (usually 1), and size. There is a new convenient syntax for writing a range: if i and j are integers then [i <=: j] is the sequence of integers starting at i and ending at j (inclusive). You can also write [i <=: j] (excludes the upper bound), [i >: j] (counts down to j, exclusive), and [i >=: j] (counts down to j, inclusive).

You can use a sequences of integers to index a sequence. The result is the sequence of the selected elements. In general (seq [i0 ... in]) is [(seq i0) ... (seq in)]. This work well with ranges: (seq [i <: j]) is the subsequence of seq from i to j (exclusive).

If the seq is a string (a CharSequence) then the result is also a string. In this case the indexing behavior is slightly different in that indexing selects (16-bit) code units, which are combined to a string.

A new dynamic type is like Object. However, it forces runtime lookup and type-checking, and supresses compile-time type check and errors. (This is similar to C#. It is useful as an escape hatch if we ever implement traditional strict static type-checking.)

Specifying the parameter type or return type of a function or method without a ’::’ is deprecated and results in a warning.

In --r7rs mode: The ’l’ exponent suffix of a number literal creates a floating-point double, rather than a BigInteger.

Added the hyperbolic functions: sinh, cosh, tanh, asinh, acosh, atanh.

The equal? function can now handle cyclic lists and vectors. So can equal-hash.

The command-line option --with-arg-count=N allows finer control of command-line-processing. It is used before an “action”, and specifies the N arguments following the action are set as the command-line-arguments. After the action, command-line-processing continues following those N arguments.

Added the R6RS module (rnrs arithmetic bitwise).

The kawa.repl argument processor now handles -D options.

The new class sub-form of import allows you to import classes, and give them abbreviated names, like the Java import statement. The new form is more compact and convenient than define-alias.

You can also use a classname directly, as a symbol, instead of writing it in the form of a list:

(import (only java.lang.Math PI))

In the only clause of the import syntax you can now directly rename, without having to write a rename clause.

Changes in the calling-convention for --full-tailcalls yields a substantial speed-up in some situations.

The type of boolean literals #f and #t is now primitive boolean rather than java.lang.Boolean.

General multi-dimensional arrays can be indexed with function call notation. E.g. (arr i j k) is equivalent to (array-ref a i j k). You can also use set! with either array-ref or function call notation.

The #!null value (Java null) is now considered false, not true. Likewise for non-canonical false Boolean objects (i.e. all instances of java.lang.Boolean for which booleanValue returns false, not just Boolean.FALSE).

New standard libraries (kawa base) and (kawa reflect).

You can now use patterns in the let form and related forms.

Implemented the lambda lifting optimzation.

An expression that has type T is now considered compatible with a context requiring an interface type I only if T implements I (or T is Object). (Before they were considered possibly-compatible if T was non-final because the run-time class might be a subclass of T that implements I.)

New --console flag forces input to be treated as an interactive console, with prompting. This is needed on Windows under Emacs, where System.console() gives the wrong result.

You can now in a sub-class reference fields from not-yet-compiled super-classes. (This doesn’t work for methods yet.)

The (? name::type value) operator supports conditional binding. The (! name::type value) operator supports unconditional binding; it is similar to define-constant, but supports patterns.

More efficient implementation of call-with-values: If either argument is a fixed-arity lambda expression it is inlined. Better type-checking of both call-with-values and values.

Jamison Hope enhanced the support for quaternions, primarily the new (kawa rotations) library.

Kawa 2.0 (December 2 2014)

There are many new features, but the big one is R7RS compatibility.

New define-alias can define aliases for static class members.

The treatment of keywords is changing to not be self-evaluating (in Scheme). If you want a literal keyword, you should quote it. Unquoted keywords should only be used for keyword arguments. (This will be enforced in a future release.) The compiler now warns about badly formed keyword arguments, for example if a value is missing following a keyword.

The default is now Java 7, rather than Java 6. This means the checked-in source code is pre-processed for Java 7, and future binary releases will require Java 7.

The behavior of parameters and fluid variables has changed. Setting a parameter no longer changes its value in already-running sub-threads. The implementation is simpler and should be more efficient.

The form define-early-constant is similar to define-constant, but it is evaluated in a module’s class initializer (or constructor in the case of a non-static definition).

Almost all of R7RS is now working:

Importing a SRFI library can now use the syntax (import (srfi N [name]))

The various standard libraries such as (scheme base) are implemented.

The functions eval and load can now take an environment-specifier. Implemented the environment function.

Extended numerator, denominator, gcd, and lcm to inexacts.

The full R7RS library functionality is working, including define-library The keyword export is now a synonym for module-export, and both support the rename keyword. The prefix option of import now works.

The cond-expand form now supports the library clause.

Implemented make-promise and delay-force (equivalent to the older name lazy).

Changed include so that by default it first seaches the directory containing the included file, so by default it has the same effect as include-relative. However, you can override the search path with the -Dkawa.include.path property. Also implemented include-ci.

Implemented define-values.

Fixed string->number to correctly handle a radix specifier in the string.

The read procedure now returns mutable pairs.

If you need to use ... in a syntax-rules template you can use (... template), which disables the special meaning of ... in template. (This is an extension of the older (... ...).)

Alternatively, you can can write (syntax-rules dots (literals) rules). The symbol dots replaces the functionality of ... in the rules.

An underscore _ in a syntax-rules pattern matches anything, and is ignored.

The syntax-error syntax (renamed from %syntax-error) allows error reporting in syntax-rules macros. (The older Kawa-specific syntax-error procedure was renamed to report-syntax-error.)

Implemented and documented R7RS exception handling: The syntax guard and the procedures with-exception-handler, raise, and raise-continuable all work. The error procedure is R7RS-compatible, and the procedures error-object?, error-object-message, error-object-irritants, file-error?, and read-error? were implemented.

Implemented emergency-exit, and modified exit so finally-blocks are executed.

Implemented exact-integer?, floor/, floor-quotient, floor-remainder, truncate/, truncate-quotient, and truncate-remainder.

The letrec* syntax is now supported. (It works the same as letrec, which is an allowed extension of letrec.)

The functions utf8->string and string->utf8 are now documented in the manual.

The changes to characters and strings are worth covering separately:

The character type is now a new primitive type (implemented as int). This can avoid boxing (object allocation)

There is also a new character-or-eof. (A union of character and the EOF value, except the latter is encoded as -1, thus avoiding object allocation.) The functions read-char and peek-char now return a character-or-eof value.

Functions like string-ref that take a character index would not take into account non-BMP characters (those whose value is greater than #xffff, thus requiring two surrogate characters). This was contrary to R6RS/R7RS. This has been fixed, though at some performance cost . (For example string-ref and string-length are no longer constant-time.)

Implemented a string-cursor API (based on Chibi Scheme). Thes allow efficient indexing, based on opaque cursors (actually counts of 16-bits chars).

Optimized string-for-each, which is now the preferred way to iterate through a string.

Implemented string-map.

New function string-append! for in-place appending to a mutable string.

New function string-replace! for replacing a substring of a string with some other string.

The SRFI-13 function string-append/shared is no longer automatically visible; you have to (import (srfi :13 strings)) or similar.

The module-name form allows the name to be a list, as in a R6RS/R7RS-style library name.

The syntax @expression is a splicing form. The expression must evaluate to a sequence (vector, list, array, etc). The function application or constructor form is equivalent to all the elements of the sequence.

The parameter object current-path returns (or sets) the default directory of the current thread.

Add convenience procedures and syntax for working with processes: run-process, process-exit-wait, process-exit-ok?, &cmd, &`, &sh.

The functions path-bytes, and path-data can read or write the entire contents of a file. Alternatively, you can use the short-hand syntax: &<{pname} &>{pname} &>>{pname}. These work with "blobs" which may be text or binary depending on context.

The initial values of (current-output-port) and (current-error-port) are now hybrid textual/binary ports. This means you can call write-bytevector and write-u8 on them, making it possible for an application to write binary data to standard output. Similarly, initial value of (current-input-port) is a hybrid textual/binary port, but only if there is no console (standard input is not a tty).

Jamison Hope contributed support for quaternions, a generalization of complex numbers containing 4 real components.

Andrea Bernardini contributed an optimized implementation of case expressions. He was sponsored by Google Summer of Code.

The kawa.sh shell script (which is installed as kawa when not configuring with --enable-kawa-frontend) now handles -D and -J options. The kawa.sh script is now also built when usint Ant.

The cond-expand features java-6 though java-9 are now set based on the System property "java.version" (rather than how Kawa was configured).

An Emacs-style coding declaration allows you to specify the encoding of a Scheme source file.

The command-line option --debug-syntax-pattern-match prints logging importation to standard error when a syntax-rules or syntax-case pattern matches.

SRFI-60 (Integers as Bits) is now fully implemented.

Ported SRFI-101. These are immutable (read-only) lists with fast (logarithmic) indexing and functional update (i.e. return a modified list). These are implemented by a RAPair class which extends the generic pair type, which means that most code that expects a standard list will work on these lists as well.

The class kawa.lib.kawa.expressions contains an experimental Scheme API for manipulating and validating expressions.

Internal: Changed representation used for multiple values to an abstract class with multiple implementations.

Internal: Started converting to more standard Java code formatting and indentation conventions, rather than GNU conventions. Some files converted; this is ongoing work.

Internal: Various I/O-related classes moved to new package gnu.kawa.io.

Various changes to the configure+make build framework: A C compiler is now only needed if you configure with --enable-kawa-frontend. Improved support for building under Windows (using MinGW/MSYS).

Support for building with GCJ was removed.

Kawa 1.14 (October 4, 2013)

You can pass flags from the kawa front-end to the java launcher using -J and -D flags. The kawa front-end now passes the kawa.command.line property to Java; this is used by the (command-line) procedure.

Various improvements to the shell-script handling, including re-written documentation.

Some initial support for Java 8.

More of R7RS is now working:

After adding list procedures make-list, list-copy, list-set! all the R7RS list procedures are implemented.

Other added procedures: square, boolean=?, string-copy!, digit-value, get-environment-variable, get-environment-variables, current-second, current-jiffy, jiffies-per-second, and features.

The predicates finite?, infinite?, and nan? are generalized to complex numbers.

The procedures write, write-simple, and write-shared are now consistent with R7RS.

String and character comparison functions are generalized to more than two arguments (but restricted to strings or characters, respectively).

The procedures string-copy, string->list, and string-fill! now take optional (start,end)-bounds. All of the R7RS string functions are now implemented.

Support => syntax in case form.

Support backslash-escaped special characters in symbols when inside vertical bars, such as '|Hello\nworld|.

The new functions and syntax are documented in the Kawa manual; look for the functions in the index.

Added define-private-alias keyword.

Extended string quasi-literals (templates) as specified by SRFI-109. For example, if name has the value "John", then:

&{Hello &[name]!}

evaluates to: "Hello John!".

Named quasi-literal constructors as specified by SRFI-108.

A symbol having the form ->type is a type conversion function that converts a value to type.

New and improved check for void-valued expressions in a context requiring a value. This is controlled by the new option --warn-void-used, which defaults to true.

The datum->syntax procedure takes an optional third parameter to specify the source location. See testsuite/srfi-108-test.scm for an example.

Instead of specifying --main the command line, you can now specify (module-compile-options: main: #t) in the Scheme file. This makes it easier to compile one or more application (main) modules along with other modules.

A change to the data structure used to detect never-returning procedure uses a lot less memory. (Kawa 1.13 implemented a conservative detection of when a procedure cannot return. This analysis would sometimes cause the Kawa compiler to run out of memory. The improved analysis uses the same basic algorithm, but with a more space-efficient “inverted” data structure.)

Multiple fixes to get Emacs Lisp (JEmacs) working (somewhat) again.

Kawa 1.13 (December 10, 2012)

We now do a simple (conservative) analysis of when a procedure cannot return. This is combined with earlier and more precise analysis of reachable code. Not only does this catch programmer errors better, but it also avoids some internal compiler errors, because Kawa could get confused by unreachable code.

Implement 2-argument version of log function, as specified by R6RS and R7RS (and, prematurely, the Kawa documentation).

Implement the R7RS bytevector functions. The bytevector type is a synonym for older u8vector type.

Implement R7RS vector procedures. Various procedures now take (start,end)-bounds.

Implement most of the R7RS input/output proecdures. Most significant enhancement is support for R7RS-conforming binary ports.

Various enhancements to the manual, including merging in lots of text from R7RS.

Improved Android support, including a more convenient Ant script contributed by Julien Rousseau. Also, documentation merged into manual.

Kawa 1.12 (May 30, 2012)

Implement a compile-time data-flow framework, similar to Single Static Assignment. This enables better type inference, improves some warnings/errors, and enables some optimizations.

Jamison Hope added support for co-variant return types and bridge methods for generics.

Macros were improved and more standards-conforming:

datum->syntax and syntax->datum are preferred names for datum->syntax-object and syntax-object->datum.

Implemented bound-identifier=? and re-wrote implementation of free-identifier=?.

Implement unsyntax and unsyntax-splicing, along with the reader prefixes #, and #,@.

New and improved lazy evaluation functionality:

Lazy values (resulting from delay or future) are implicitly forced as needed. This makes “lazy programming” more convenient.

New type promise.

The semantics of promises (delay etc) is now compatible with SRFI 45.

“Blank promises” are useful for passing data between processes, logic programmming, and more. New functions promise-set-value!, promise-set-alias!, promise-set-exception!, and promise-set-thunk!.

The stream functions of SRFI-41 were re-implemented to use the new promise functionality.

Different functions in the same module can be compiled with or without full tailcall support. You can control this by using full-tailcalls in with-compile-options. You can also control full-tailcalls using module-compile-options.

Charles Turner (sponsored by Google’s Summer of Code) enhanced the printer with support for SRFI-38: External Representation for Data With Shared Structure.

Optimize tail-recursion in module-level procedures. (We used to only do this for internal functions, for reasons that are no longer relevant.)

Add support for building Kawa on Windows using configure+make (autotools) and Cygwin.

Some support for parameterized (generic) types:

  Type[Arg1 Arg2 ... ArgN]

is more-or-less equivalent to Java’s:

  Type<Arg1, Arg2, ..., ArgN>

New language options --r5rs, --r6rs, and --r7rs provide better compatibility with those Scheme standards. (This is a work-in-progress.) For example --r6rs aims to disable Kawa extensions that conflict with R6RS. It does not aim to disable all extensions, only incompatible extensions. So far these extensions disable the colon operator and keyword literals. Selecting --r5rs makes symbols by default case-insensitive.

The special tokens #!fold-case and #!no-fold-case act like comments except they enable or disable case-folding of symbols. The old symbol-read-case global is now only checked when a LispReader is created, not each time a symbol is read.

You can now use square brackets to construct immutable sequences (vectors).

A record type defined using define-record-type is now compiled to a class that is a member of the module class.

Annotations are now supported. This example shows how to use JAXB annotations to automatically convert between between Java objects and XML files.

Prevent mutation of vector literals.

More R6RS procedures: vector-map, vector-for-each, string-for-each, real-valued?, rational-valued?, integer-valued?, finite?, infinite?, nan?, exact-integer-sqrt.

SRFI-14 ("character sets") and SRFI-41 ("streams") are now supported, thanks to porting done by Jamison Hope.

Kawa now runs under JDK 1.7. This mostly involved fixing some errors in StackMapTable generation.

You can now have a class created by define-simple-class with the same name as the module class. For example (define-simple-class foo ...) in a file foo.scm. The defined class will serve dual-purpose as the module class.

Improvements in separating compile-time from run-time code, reducing the size of the runtime jar used for compiled code.

In the cond-expand conditional form you can now use class-exists:ClassName as a feature “name” to tests that ClassName exists.

Kawa 1.11 (November 11, 2010)

A new Kawa logo, contributed by Jakub Jankiewicz.

A new --warn-unknown-member option, which generalizes --warn-invoke-unknown-method to fields as well as methods.

A new kawac task, useful for Ant build.xml files, contributed by Jamison Hope.

Updated Android support.

New define-enum macro contributed by Jamison Hope.

Access specifiers 'final and 'enum are now allowed in define-class and related forms.

Optimized odd? and even?.

If you specify the type of a #!rest parameter as an array type, that will now be used for the "varargs" method parameter. (Before only object arrays did this.)

When constructing an object and there is no matching constructor method, look for "add" methods in addition to "set" methods. Also, allow passing constructor args as well as keyword setters. See here for the gory details.

New expand function (contributed by Helmut Eller, and enabled by (require 'syntax-utils)) for converting Scheme expressions to macro-expanded forms.

SAM-conversion: In a context that expects a Single Abstract Method (SAM) type (for example java.lang.Runnable), if you pass a lambda you will get an object where the lambda implements the abstract method.

In interactive mode allow dynamic rebinding of procedures. I.e. if you re-define a procedure, the old procedure objects gets modified in-place and re-used, rather than creating a new procedure object. Thus calls in existing procedures will call the new version.

Fix various threading issues related to compilation and eval.

When format returns a string, return a java.lang.String rather than a gnu.lists.FString. Also, add some minor optimization.

Inheritance of environments and fluid variables now work properly for all child threads, not just ones created using future.

Kawa 1.10 (July 24, 2010)

Now defaults to using Java 6, when compiling from source. The pre-built jar works with Java 5, but makes use of some Java 6 features (javax.script, built-in HTTP server) if available.

You can write XML literals in Scheme code prefixed by a #, for example:

#<p>The result is &{result}.</p>

New functions element-name and attribute-name.

Various Web server improvements. You have the option of using JDK 6’s builtin web-server for auto-configued web pages. Automatic import of web server functions, so you should not need to (import 'http) any more.

Kawa hashtables now extend java.util.Map.

If a source file is specified on the kawa command line without any options, it is read and compiled as a whole module before it is run. In contrast, if you want to read and evaluate a source file line-by-line you must use the -f flag.

You can specify a class name on the kawa command line:

$ kawa fully.qualified.name

This is like the java command. but you don’t need to specify the path to the Kawa runtime library, and you don’t need a main method (as long as the class is Runnable).

The usual bug-fixes, including better handling of the ~F format directive; and fix in handling of macro hygiene of the lambda (bug #27042).

Spaces are now optional before and after the ’::’ in type specifiers. The preferred syntax leave no space after the ’::’, as in:

(define xx ::int 1)

define-for-syntax and begin-for-syntax work.

You can now use car, cdr etc to work with syntax objects that wrap lists, as in SRFI-72.

You can now define a package alias:

(define-alias jutil java.util)
(define mylist :: jutil:List (jutil:ArrayList))

--module-static is now the default. A new --module-nonstatic (or --no-module-static) option can be used to get the old behavior.

You can use access: to specify that a field is 'volatile or 'transient.

You can now have type-specifiers for multiple variables in a do.

Imported variables are read-only.

Exported variables are only made into Locations when needed.

The letter used for the exponent in a floating-point literal determines its type: 12s2 is a java.lang.Float, 12d2 is a java.lang.Double, 12l2 is a java.math.BigInteger, 12e2 is a gnu.math.DFloat.

Internal: Asking for a .class file using getResourceAsStream on an ArrayClassLoader will now open a ByteArrayInputStream on the class bytes.

A new disassemble function.

If exp1 has type int, the type of (+ exp1 1) is now (32-bit) int, rather than (unlimited-precision) integer. Similar for long expressions, other arithmetic operations (as appropriate), and other untyped integer literals (as long as they fit in 32/64 bits respectively).

Many more oprimization/specializations of arithmetic, especially when argument types are known.

Top-level bindings in a module compiled with --main are now implicitly module-private, unless there is an explicit module-export.

SRFI-2 (and-let*: an and with local bindings, a guarded * special form) is now supported.

The reader now supports shared sub-objects, as in SRFI-38 and Common Lisp: (#2=(3 4) 9 #2# #2#). (Writing shared sub-objects is not yet implemented.)

A module compiled with --main by default exports no bindings (unless overriden by an explicit module-export).

Factor out compile-time only code from run-time code. The new kawart-version.jar is smaller because it has less compile-time only code. (Work in progress.)

More changes for R6RS compatibility:

The reader now recognizes +nan.0, +inf.0 and variations.

The div, mod, div0, mod0, div-and-mod, div0-and-mod0, inexact and exact functions were implemented.

command-line and exit.

Kawa 1.9.90 (August 8, 2009)

Support for javax.script.

Support for regular expressions.

Performance improvements:

Emit iinc instruction (to increment a local int by a constant).

Inline the not function if the argument is constant.

If call-with-current-continuation is only used to exit a block in the current method, optimize to a goto.

Generate StackMapTable attributes when targeting Java 6.

Kawa can now inline a function with multiple calls (without code duplication) if all call sites have the same return location (continuation). For example: (if p (f a) (f b)). Also mutually tail-recursive functions are inlined, so you get constant stack space even without --full-tailcalls. (Thanks for Helmut Eller for a prototype.)

A number of changes for R6RS compatibility:

The char-titlecase, char-foldcase, char-title-case? library functions are implemented.

Imported variables are read-only.

Support the R6RS import keyword, including support for renaming.

Support the R6RS export keyword (though without support for renaming).

Implemented the (rnrs hashtables) library.

Implemented the (rnrs sorting) library.

CommonLisp-style keyword syntax is no longer supported (for Scheme): A colon followed by an identifier is no longer a keyword (though an identifier followed by a colon is still a keyword). (One reason for this change is to support SRFI-97.)

The character names #\delete, #\alarm, #\vtab are now supported. The old names #\del, #\rubout, and #\bel are deprecated.

Hex escapes in character literals are supported. These are now printed where we before printed octal escapes.

A hex escape in a string literal should be terminated by a semi-colon, but for compatibily any other non-hex-digit will also terminate the escape. (A terminating semi-colon will be skipped, though a different terminator will be included in the string.)

A backslash-whitespace escape in a string literal will not only ignore the whitespace through the end of the line, but also any initial whitespace at the start of the following line.

The comment prefix #; skips the following S-expression, as specified by SRFI-62.

All the R6RS exact bitwise arithmetic functions are now implemented and documented in the manual. The new standard functions (for example bitwise-and) are now preferred over the old functions (for example logand).

If delete-file fails, throws an exception instead of returning #f.

The code-base now by default assumes Java 5 (JDK 1.5 or newer), and pre-built jar files will require Java 5. Also, the Kawa source code now uses generics, so you need to use a generics-aware javac, passing it the appropriate --target flag.

New SRFIs supported:

SRFI-62 - S-expression comments.

SRFI-64 - Scheme API for test suites.

SRFI-95 - Sorting and Merging.

SRFI-97 - Names for SRFI Libraries. This is a naming convention for R6RS import statements to reference SRFI libraries.

In BRL text outside square brackets (or nested like ]this[) now evaluates to UnescapedData, which a Scheme quoted string evaluates to String, rather than an FString. (All of the mentioned types implement java.lang.CharSequence.)

You can now run Kawa Scheme programs on Android, Google’s mobile-phone operating system.

The macro resource-url is useful for accessing resources.

A new command-line option --target (or -target) similar to javac’s -target option.

If there is no console, by default create a window as if -w was specificed.

If a class method (defined in define-class, define-simple-class or object) does not have its parameter or return type specified, search the super-classes/interfaces for matching methods (same name and number of parameters), and if these are consistent, use that type.

Trying to modify the car or cdr of a literal list now throws an exception.

The .zip archive created by compile-file is now compressed.

Java5-style varargs-methods are recognized as such.

When evaluating or loading a source file, we now always compile to bytecode, rather than interpreting “simple” expressions. This makes semantics and performance more consistent, and gives us better exception stack traces.

The Scheme type specifier <integer> now handles automatic conversion from java.math.BigInteger and the java.lang classes Long, Integer, Short, and Byte. The various standard functions that work on <integer> (for example gcd and arithmetic-shift) can be passed (say) a java.lang.Integer. The generic functions such as + and the real function modulo should also work. (The result is still a gnu.math.IntNum.)

If a name such as (java.util) is lexically unbound, and there is a known package with that name, return the java.lang.Package instance. Also, the colon operator is extended so that package:name evaluates to the Class for package.name.

`prefix:,expression works - it finds a symbol in prefix’s package (aka namespace), whose local-name is the value of expression.

A quantity 3.0cm is now syntactic sugar for (* 3.0 unit:cm). Similarly: (define-unit name value) is equivalent to: (define-constant unit:name value) This means that unit names follow normal name-lookup rules (except being in the unit “package”), so for example you can have local unit definitions.

You can specify whether a class has public or package access, and whether it is translated to an interface or class.

You can declare an abstract method by writing #!abstract as its body.

If a name of the form type? is undefined, but type is defined, then treat the former as (lambda (x) (instance? x type)).

A major incompatible (but long-sought) change: Java strings (i.e. java.lang.String values) are now Scheme strings, rather than Scheme symbols. Since Scheme strings are mutable, while Java Strings are not, we use a different type for mutable strings: gnu.lists.FString (this is not a change). Scheme string literals are java.lang.String values. The common type for Scheme string is java.lang.CharSequence (which was introducted in JDK 1.4).

Scheme symbols are now instances of gnu.mapping.Symbol, specifically the SimpleSymbol class.

A fully-qualified class name such as java.lang.Integer now evaluates to the corresponding java.lang.Class object. I.e. it is equivalent to the Java term java.lang.Integer.class. This assumes that the name does not have a lexical binding, and that it exists in the class-path at compile time.

Array class names (such as java.lang.Integer[]) and primitive types (such as int) also work.

The older angle-bracket syntax <java.lang.Integer> also works and has the same meaning. It also evaluates to a Class. It used to evaluate to a Type, so this is a change.

The name bound by a define-simple-class now evaluates to a Class, rather than a ClassType. A define-simple-class is not allowed to reference non-static module-level bindings; for that use define-class.

New convenience macro define-syntax-case.

Kawa 1.9.1 (January 23, 2007)

Fix some problems building Kawa from source using configure+make.

Kawa 1.9.0 (January 21, 2007)

New types and functions for working with paths and URIs.

Reader macros URI, namespace, duration.

Simplified build using gcj, and added configure flag –with-gcj-dbtool.

If two “word” values are written, a space is written between them. A word is most Scheme values, including numbers and lists. A Scheme string is treated as a word by write but by not display.

A new --pedantic command-line flag. It currently only affects the XQuery parser.

The load-compile procedure was removed.

The string printed by the --version switch now includes the Subversion revision and date (but only if Kawa was built using make rather than ant from a checked-out Subversion tree).

Kawa development now uses the Subversion (svn) version control system instead of CVS.

Show file/line/column on unbound symbols (both when interpreted and when compiled).

Cycles are now allowed between require’d modules. Also, compiling at set of modules that depend on each other can now specified on the compilation command line in any order, as long as needed require forms are given.

The “colon notation” has been generalized.. The syntax object:name generally means to extract a component with a given name from object, which may be an object, a class, or a namespace.

New command-line options --debug-error-prints-stack-trace and --debug-warning-prints-stack-trace provide stack trace on static error messages.

The license for the Kawa software has been changed to the X11/MIT license.

A much more convenient syntax for working with Java arrays.

The same function-call syntax also works for Scheme vectors, uniform vectors, strings, lists - and anything else that implements java.util.List.

The fields and methods of a class and its bases classes are in scope within methods of the class.

Unnamed procedures (such as lambda expressions) are printed with the source filename and line.

The numeric compare functions (=, <=, etc) and number->string now work when passed standard Java Number objects (such as java.lang.Long or java.math.BigDecimal).

SRFI-10 is now implemented, providing the #,(name args ...) form. Predefined constructor names so far are URI and namespace. The define-reader-ctor function is available if you (require 'srfi-10).

A new --script option makes it easier to write Unix shell scripts.

Allow general URLs for loading (including the -f flag), compilation and open-input-file, if the “file name” starts with a URL “scheme” like http:.

Classes defined (e.g. with define-simple-class) in a module can now mutually reference each other. On the other hand, you can no longer define-class if the class extends a class rather than an interface; you must use define-simple-class.

KawaPageServlet now automatically selects language.

provide macro.

quasisyntax and the convenience syntax #`, from SRFI-72.

define-for-syntax, syntax-source, syntax-line, and syntax-column, for better compatibility with mzscheme.

SRFI-34 (Exception Handling for Programs), which implements with-exception-handler, guard, and raise, is now available, if you (require 'srfi-34). Also, SRFI-35 (Conditions) is available, if you (require 'srfi-35).

The case-lambda form from SRFI-16 is now implemented more efficiently.

Kawa 1.8 (October 18, 2005)

SRFI-69 “Basic hash tables” is now available, if you (require 'hash-table) or (require 'srfi-69). This is an optimized and Java-compatible port whose default hash function calls the standard hashCode method.

A define-simple-class can now have one (or more) explicit constructor methods. These have the spcial name *init*. You can call superclass constructors or sibling constructors (this constructor calls) using the (admittedly verbose but powerful) invoke-special form.

The runnable function creates a Runnable from a Procedure. It is implemented using the new class RunnableClosure, which is now also used to implement future.

The kawa command can now be run “in-place” from the build directory: $build_dir/bin/kawa.

The special field name class in (static-name type 'class) or (prefix:.class) returns the java.lang.Class object corresponding to the type or prefix. This is similar to the Java syntax.

Contructing an instance (perhaps using make) of a class defined using define-simple-class in the current module is much more efficient, since it no longer uses reflection. (Optimizing classes defined using define-class is more difficult.) The constructor function defined by the define-record-type macro is also optimized.

You can now access instance methods using this short-hand: (*:methodname instance arg ...) This is equivalent to: (invoke instance 'methodname arg ...)

You can now also access a fields using the same colon-notation as used for accessing methods, except you write a dot before the field name: (type:.fieldname) ;; is like: (static-field type 'fieldname). (*:.fieldname instance) ;; is like: (field 'fieldname instance) (type:.fieldname instance) ;; is like: (*:.fieldname (as instance type)) These all work with set! - for example: (set! (*:.fieldname instance) value).

In the above uses of colon-notation, a type can be any one of: - a namespace prefix bound using define-namespace to a namespace uri of the form "class:classname"; - a namespace prefix using define-namespace bound to a <classname> name, which can be a fully-qualified class name or a locally-declared class, or an alias (which might be an imported class); - a fully qualified name of a class (that exists at compile-time), as in (java.lang.Integer:toHexString 123); or - a <classname> variable, for example: (<list>:list3 11 12 13).

New fluid variables *print-base*, *print-radix*, *print-right-margin*, and *print-miser-width* can control output formatting. (These are based on Common Lisp.)

You can new emit elipsis (...) in the output of a syntax template using the syntax (... ...), as in other syntax-case implementations.

The args-fold program-argument processor from SRFI-37 is available after you (require 'args-fold) or (require 'srfi-37).

The fluid-let form now works with lexical bindings, and should be more compatible with other Scheme implementations.

(module-export namespace:prefix) can be used to export a namespace prefix.

Static modules are now implemented more similarly to non-static modules. Specifically, the module body is not automatically run by the class initializer. To get the old behavior, use the new --module-static-run flag. Alternatively, instead of (module-static #t) use (module-static 'init-run).

Implement SRFI-39 "Parameter-objects". These are like anonymous fluid values and use the same implementation. current-input-port, current-output-port, and current-error-port are now parameters.

Infer types of variables declared with a let.

Character comparisons (such as char-=?, char-ci<?) implemented much more efficiently — and (if using Java5) work for characters not in the Basic Multilingual Plane.

Major re-write of symbol and namespace handling. A Symbol is now immutable, consisting of a "print-name" and a pointer to a Namespace (package). An Environment is a mapping from Symbol to Location.

Rename Interpreter to Language and LispInterpreter to LispLanguage.

Constant-time property list operations.

Namespace-prefixes are now always resolved at compile-time, never at run-time.

(define-namespace PREFIX <CLASS>) is loosely the same as (define-namespace PREFIX "class:CLASS") but does the right thing for classes defined in this module, including nested or non-simple classes.

Macros capture proper scope automatically, not just when using require. This allows some internal macros to become private.

Major re-write of the macro-handling and hygiene framework. Usable support for syntax-case; in fact some of the primitives (such as if) are now implemented using syntax-case. (syntax form) (or the short-cut #!form) evaluates to a syntax object. (define-syntax (mac x) tr) same as (define-syntax mac (lambda (x) tr)). The following non-hygienic forms are equivalent:

  (define-macro (macro-name (param ...) transformer)
  (define-macro macro-name (lambda (param ...) transformer))
  (defmacro macro-name (PARAM ...) transformer)

Allow vectors and more general ellipsis-forms in patterns and templates.

A new configure switch --with-java-source=version allows you to tweak the Kawa sources to match Java compiler and libraries you’re using. The default (and how the sources are distributed) is 2 (for "Java 2" – jdk 1.2 or better), but you can also select "1" (for jdk 1.1.x), and "5" for Java 5 (jdk 1.5). You can also specify a jdk version number: "1.4.1" is equivalent to "2" (for now). Note the default source-base is incompatible with Java 5 (or more generally JAXB 1.3 or DOM 3), unless you also --disable-xml.

Configure argument --with-servlet[=servlet-api.jar] replaces --enable-servlet.

Function argument in error message are now numbered starting at one. Type errors now give better error messages.

A new function calling convention, used for --full-tailcalls. A function call is split up in two parts: A match0/.../matchN method checks that the actual arguments match the expected formal arguments, and leaves them in the per-thread CallContext. Then after the calling function returns, a zero-argument apply() methods evaluates the function body. This new convention has long-term advantages (performance, full continuations), but the most immediate benefit is better handling of generic (otherloaded) functions. There are also improved error messages.

Real numbers, characters, Lisp/Scheme strings (FString) and symbols all now implement the Comparable interface.

In define-class/define-simple-class: [Most of this work was funded by Merced Systems.]

You can specify access: ['private|'protected|'public|'package] to set the Java access permissions of fields and methods.

Methods can be static by using the access: 'static specifier.

The reflective routines invoke , field , static-field , slot-ref , slot-set! can now access non-public methods/fields when appropriate.

Such classes are no longer initialized when the containing module is loaded.

The expr in init-form: expr is now evaluated in the outer scope.

A new init: expr evalues expr in the inner scope.

An option name following allocation: can now be a string literal or a quoted symbol. The latter is preferred: allocation: 'class.

Added 'static as a synonym for 'class following allocation:.

Initialization of static field (allocation: 'class init: expr) now works, and is performed at class initialization time.

You can use unnamed “dummy fields” to add initialization-time actions not tied to a field:

  (define-simple-class Foo ()
    (:init (perform-some-action)))

Kawa 1.7.90 (2003)

Various fixes and better error messages in number parsing. Some optimizations for the divide function.

New framework for controlling compiler warnings and other features, supporting command-line flags, and the Scheme forms with-compile-options and module-compile-options. The flag --warn-undefined-variable is useful for catching typos. Implementation funded by Merced Systems.

New invoke-special syntax form (implemented by Chris Dean).

New define-variable form (similar to Common Lisp’s defvar).

Kawa 1.7 (June 7, 2003)

KawaPageServlet allows automatic loading and on-the-fly compilation in a servlet engine. See http://www.gnu.org/software/qexo/simple-xquery-webapp.html.

The default source-base requires various Java 2 features, such as collection. However, make-select1 will comment out Java2 dependencies, allowing you to build Kawa with an older Java implementation.

The -f flag and the load function can take an absolute URL. New Scheme functions load-relative and base-uri.

Imported implementation of cut and cute from SRFI-26 (Notation for Specializing Parameters without Currying).

The way top-level definitions (including Scheme procedures) are mapped into Java fields is changed to use a mostly reversible mapping. (The mapping to method names remains more natural but non-reversible.)

define-alias of types can now be exported from a module.

New --no-inline and --inline=none options.

You can use define-namespace to define “namespace aliases”. This is used for the new short-hard syntax for method invocation: (define-namespace Int32 "class:java.lang.Integer") (Int32:toHexString 255) => "ff" (Int32:toString (Int32:new "00255")) => "255" Alternatively, you can write: (java.lang.Integer:toHexString 255) => "ff"

SRFI-9 (define-record-type) has been implemented, and compiled to a define-class, with efficient code.

The configure option --with-collections is now the default.

Unknowns are no longer automatically static.

If type not specified in a declaration, don’t infer it from it initial value. If no return type is specified for a function, default to Object, rather than the return type of the body. (The latter leads to undesirable different behaviour if definitions are re-arranged.)

You can now define and use classes defined using object, define-class, and define-simple-class from the “interpreter”, as well as the compiler. Also, a bug where inherited fields did not get initialized has been fixed.

There are several new procedures useful for servlets.

Numerical comparisions (<, <=, etc) now generates optimized bytecode if the types of the operands have certain known types. including efficient code for <int>, <long>, <double>, and <integer>. Much more code can now (with type declaration) be written just as efficiently in Scheme as in Java.

There have been some internal re-arranging of how Expressions are processed. The Scheme-specific Translator type now inherits from Compilation, which replaces the old Parser class. A Complation is now allocated much earlier, as part of parsing, and includes a SourceMessages object. SourcesMessages now includes (default) line number, which is used by Compilation for the "current" line numbers. The ExpWalker class includes a SourceMessages instance (which it gets from the Compilation). CanInline.inline method now takes ExpWalker parameter. Checking of the number or parameters, and mapping known procedures to Java methods are now both done during the inlining pass.

The user-visible effect is that Kawa can now emit error mesages more cleanly more places; the inlining pass can be more agressive, and can emit better error messages, which yields better type information. This gives us better code with fewer warnings about unknown methods.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.98 to 1.6.99.

A new language front-end handles a tiny subset of XSLT. An example is the check-format-users test in gnu/xquery/testsuite/Makefile.

There are now converters between SAX2 and Consumer events, and a basic implementation of XMLReader based on XMLParser.

The function as-xml prints a value in XML format.

Srfi-0 (cond-expand), srfi-8 (receive), and srfi-25 (multi-dimensional arrays) are now implemented. So is srfi-1 (list library), though that requires doing (require ’list-lib).

The JEmacs code is being re-organized, splitting out the Swing-dependent code into a separate gnu.jemacs.swing package. This should make it easier to add JEmacs implementation without Swing.

The class gnu.expr.Interpreter has various new ’eval’ methods that are useful for evaluating Scheme/BRL/XQuery/... expressions from Java.

Kawa now uses current versions of autoconf, autoamke, and libtool, allowing the use of automake file inclusion.

The comparisons <<, <=, -, >, and => now compile to optimized Java arithmetic if both operands are <int> or a literal that fits in <int>.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.97 to 1.6.98

Generated HTML and Postscrpt documents are no longer included in the source distribution. Get kawa-doc-version.tar.gz instead.

(format #t ...) and (format PORT ...) now returns #!void instead of #t.

Support fluid bindings (fluid-let) for any thread, not just Future and main.

A Unix script header #!/PROGRAM is ignored.

You can now take the same Kawa "web" program (written in Scheme, KRL/BRL, or XQuery) and run it as either a servlet or a CGI script.

There are a number of new functions for accessing HTTP requests and generating HTTP responses.

Kawa now supports a new experimental programming KRL (the "Kawa Report Language"). You select this language using –krl on the Kawa command link. It allows Scheme code to be inside template files, like HTML pages, using a syntax based on BRL (brl.sourceforge.net). However, KRL has soem experimental changes to both BRL and standard Scheme. There is also a BRL-compatibile mode, selected using –brl, though that currently only supports a subset of BRL functions.

If language is not explicitly specified and you’re running a source file (e.g. "java kawa.repl myscript.xql"), Kawa tried to derive the language from the the filename extension (e.g. "xql"). It still defaults to Scheme if there is no extension or the extension is unrecognized.

New command-line option –output-format alias –format can be used to over-ride the format used to write out top-level (repl, load) values.

XMLPrinter can now print in (non-well-formed-XML) HTML.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.96 to 1.6.97

Changed lots of error messages to use pairs of single quotes rather than starting with a backquote (accent grave): ’name’ instead of ‘name’. Many newer fonts make the latter look bad, so it is now discouraged.

The types <String> and <java.lang.String> new behave differently. The type <java.lang.String> now works just like (say) <java.util.Hashtable>. Converting an object to a <java.lang.String> is done by a simple coercion, so the incoming value must be a java.lang.String reference or null. The special type <String> converts any object to a java.string.String by calling toString; it also handles null by specially testing for it.

For convenience (and backwards compatibility) Kawa uses the type <String> (rather than <java.lang.String>) when it sees the Java type java.lang.String, for example in the argument to an invoke.

The default behaviour of ’[’ and ’] was changed back to be token (word) constituents, matching R5RS and Common Lisp. However, you can easily change this behaviour using the new setBrackMode method or the defaultBracketMode static field in ReadTable.

You can now build Kawa from source using the Ant build system (from Apache’s Jakarta project), as an alternative to using the traditional configure+make system. An advantage of Ant is that it works on most Java systems, without requiring a Unix shell and commands. Specifically, this makes it easy to build Kawa under MS-Windows. Thanks to James White for contributing this support.

Added (current-error-port) which does the obvious.

The new let-values and let-values* macros from srfi-11 provide a more convenient way to use multiple values.

All the abstract apply* and eval* methods now specify ’throws Throwable’. A bunch of code was changed to match. The main visible advantage is that the throw and primitive-throw procedures work for any Throwable without requiring it to be (confusingly) wrapped.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.95 to 1.6.96

A new compilation flag –servlet generates a Servlet which can be deployed in a servlet engin like Tomcat. This is experimental, but it seesm to work for both Scheme source and XQuery source.

The interface gnu.lists.CharSequence was renamed to avoid conflitcs with the (similar) interface java.lang.CharSequence in JDK 1.4beta.

New –help option (contributed by Andreas Schlapbach).

Changed the code generation used when –full-tailcalls. It now is closer to that used by default, in that we don’t generate a class for each non-inlined procedure. In both cases calling an unknown procedure involves executing a switch statement to select a method. In addition to generating fewer classes and simplifying one of the more fragile parts of Kawa, it is also a step towards how full continuations will be implemented.

Changed the convention for name "mangling" - i.e. how Scheme names are mapped into Java names. Now, if a Scheme name is a valid Java name it is used as is; otherwise a reversible mangling using "$" characters is used. Thus the Scheme names '< and '$Leq are both mapped into the same Java name "$Leq". However, other names not containing "$" should no longer clash, including pairs like "char-letter?" and "charLetter?" and "isCharLetter" which used to be all mapped to "isCharLetter". Now only names containing "$" can be ambiguous.

If the compiler can determine that all the operands of (+ ...) or (- ...) are floating-point, then it will generate optimized code using Java primitive arithmetic.

Guile-style keyword syntax ’#:KEYWORD’ is recognized. (Note this conflicts with Common Lisp syntax for uninterned symbols.)

New syntax forms define-class and define-simple-class allow you to define classes more easily. define-class supports true multiple inheritance and first class class values, where each Scheme class is compiled to a pair of an inteface and a class. define-simple-class generates more efficient and Java-compatible classes.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.94 to 1.6.95.

A new language "xquery" implements a (so far small subset of) XQuery, the draft XML Query languaage.

Various internal (Java API) changes: Changes to gnu.expr.Interpreter to make it easier to add non-Lisp-like languages; gnu.lists.Consumer now has an endAttribute method that need to be called after each attribute, rather than endAttributes that was called after all of them.

If configured with –with-gcj, Kawa builds and intalls a ’gckawa’ script to simlify linking with needed libraries.

The setter function is now inlined, and (set! (field X 'N) V) and (set! (static-field <T> "N) V) are now inlined.

If configured --with-gcj, then a gckawa helper script is installed, to make it easier to link Kawa+gcj-compiled applications.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.92 to 1.6.94

The JEmacs code now depends on CommonLisp, rather than vice versa, which means Commonlisp no longer depends on Swing, and can be built with GCJ. CommonLisp and JEmacs symbols are now implemented using Binding, not String.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.90 to 1.6.92

Kawa now installs as a .jar file (kawa.jar symlinked to kawa-VERSION.jar), rather than a collection of .class files.

The Kawa manual includes instructions for how to build Kawa using GCJ, and how to compile Scheme code to a native executable using GCJ.

Kawa now has builtin pretty-printer support, using an algorithm from Steel Bank Common Lisp converted from Lisp to Java. The high-level Common Lisp pretty-printing features are mostly not yet implemented, but the low-level support is there. The standard output and error ports default to pretty-printing.

A new formatting framework uses the Consumer interface from gnu.lists. You can associate a format with an output port. Common Lisp and JEmacs finally print using their respective syntaxes.

All output ports (OutPort instances) are now automatically flushed on program exit, using a new WriterManager helper class.

The new commmand-line option –debug-print-expr causes the Expression for each expression to be printed. The option –debug-print-final-expr is similar, but prints Expressions after optimization and just before compilation. They are printed using the new pretty-printer.

Changed calling convention for –full-tailcalls to write results to a Consumer, usually a TreeList or something to be printed. A top-level ModuleBody now uses the same CpsProcedure convention. This is useful for generating xml or html.

New libtool support allows kawa to be built as a shared library.

The new configure flag –with-gcj uses gcj to compile Kawa to both .class files and native code. This is experimental.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.70 to 1.6.90

The reader (for Scheme and Lisp) has been re-written to be table-driven, based on the design of Common Lisp readtables.

The new gnu.lists package has new implementations of sequence-related classes. It replaces most of gnu.kawa.util. See the package.html file.

If the expected type of a non-unary + or - is <int> or <long> and the operands are integeral types, then the operands will converted to the primitive integer type and the addition or subtraction done using primitive arithmetic. Similarly if the expected type is <float> or <long> and the operands have appropriate type. This optimization an make a big performance difference. (We still need to also optimize compare operations like (< x y) to really benefit from <int> declarations of loop variables.)

The implementation of procedure closures has been changed to basically be the same as top-level procedures (except when –full-tailcalls is specified): Each procedure is now an instance of a ModuleMethod, which each "frame" is an instance of ModuleBody, just like for top-level functions. This sometimes reduces the number of classes generated, but more importantly it simplifies the implementation.

A new gnu.xml package contains XML-related code, currently an XML parser and printer, plus some XPath support. The class gnu.lists.TreeList (alias <document>) is useful for compactly representing nested structures, including XML documents. If you (require 'xml) you will get Scheme interfaces (print-as-xml and parse-xml-from-url) to these classes.

New package gnu.kawa.functions, for primitive functions (written in Java).

The map and for-each procedure is now inlined. This is most especially beneficial when it allows the mapped-over procedure to also be inlined, such as when that procedure is a lambda expression.

Added documentation on compiling with Jikes. Renamed some classes to avoid warning when compiling with Jikes.

The reverse! procedure was added.

Internal changes: * If a variable reference is unknown, create a Declaration instance with the IS_UNKNOWN flag to represent an imported binding. * The ExpWalker framework for "tree walking" Expressions had a bit of reorganization. * New package gnu.kawa.functions, for primitive functions (written in Java).

Added a hook for constant-folding and other optimization/inlining at traversal (ExpWalker) time. Optimization of + and - procedures to use primitive Java operations when the operands are primitive types.

Implementation of SRFI-17. Change the definitions of (set! (f x ...) val) to ((setter f) x ... val), rather then the old ((setter f) val x ...). You can now associate a setter with a procedure, either using make-procedure or set-procedure-property!. Also, (setter f) is now inlined, when possible.

Internally, Syntax (and hence Macro) no longer extend Declaration.

Various Java-level changes, which may be reflected in Scheme later: * gnu.kawa.util.Consumer interface is similar to ObjectOutput and SAX’s ContentHandler interfaces. * A gnu.expr.ConsumerTarget is used when evaluating to an implicit Consumer. * These interfaces will make it easy to write functional-style but efficient code for transforming data streams, including XML. * gnu.kawa.util.FString is now variable-size.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.68 to 1.6.70

The bare beginnings of Common Lisp support, enabled by the –commonlisp (or –clisp) command line option. This is so far little more than a hack of the EmacsLisp support, but with lexical scoping and CL-style format.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.66 to 1.6.68

JEmacs news:

Define emacs-version as Kawa version but with leading 0 instead of 1. For example, the current value is "0.6.68 JEmacs".

New testsuite directory.

Improved autoload framework. Handle ELisp autoload comments.

Handle escape and meta-key.

Handle lot more of ELisp.

Lots more is now done in ELisp, using .el files imported from XEmacs.

Incomplete support for setting mark, including using selection.

Basic (but incomplete) implementation of (interactive spec).

Common Lisp extensions: typep, default arguments.

A new status.html file to note what works and what doesn’t.

You can now specify in define and define-private the type of a variable. If the variable is module-level, (define name :: <type> value) creates a field named “name” having the specified type and initial value. (If type is not specified, the default is not Object, but rather a Binding that contains the variable’s value.)

You can now define the type of a module-level variable: In (define[-private] :: type expression) New (define-constant name [:: type] expression) definition form.

A procedure can now have arbitrary properties associated with it. Use procedure-property and set-procedure-property! to get and set them.

The new procedure make-procedure creates a generic procedure that may contain one or more methods, as well as specified properties.

New declaration form define-base-unit. Both it and define-unit have been re-implemented to be module-safe. Basically ’(define-unit ft 12in)’ is sugar for ’(define-constant ft$unit (... (* 12 in$unit)))’, where ft$unit and in$unit are standard identifiers managed by the module system. Also, the output syntax for units and quantities is cleaner.

The new declaration (module-export name ...) allows control over the names exported from a module. The new declaration (module-static ...) allows control over which definitions are static and which are non-static. This makes it easier to use a module as a Java class.

Procedures names that accidentally clash with inherited method names (such as "run") are now re-named.

Simple aliases (define-aliases defining an alias for a variable name) are implemented more efficiently.

The package hierarchy is getter cleaner, with fewer cyclic dependencies: The gnu.math package no longer has any dependencies on kawa.* or gnu.*. Two classes were moved from gnu.text to other classes, avoiding another cyclic package dependency between gnu.text and gnu.mapping. The new gnu.kawa.lispexpr is for compile-time handling of Lisp-like languages.

Compliation of literals has been re-done. A class that can be used in a literal no longer needs to be declared as Compilable. Instead, you declare it as implementaing java.io.Externalizable, and make sure it has appropriate methods.

All the standard "data" types (i.e. not procedures or ports) now implement java.io.Externalizable, and can thus be serialized. If they appear in literals, they can also be compiled.

Created a new class gnu.kawa.util.AbstractString, with the Scheme alias <abstract-string>. The old gnu.kawa.util.FString now extends AbstractString. A new class CharBuffer provides an growable buffer, with markers (automatically-adjusted positions). Many of the Scheme <string> procedures now work on <abstract-string>. The JEmacs BufferContnat class (contains the characters of a buffer) now extends CharBuffer.

Some JEmacs changes to support a "mode" concept, as well as preliminary support for inferior-process and telnet modes.

New section in manual / web page for projects using Kawa.

The record feasture (make-record-type etc) how handles "funny" type and fields names that need to be "mangled" to Java names.

Re-did implementation of define-alias. For example, you can define type-aliases: (define-alias <marker> <gnu.jemacs.buffer.Marker>) and then use <marker> instead of <gnu.jemacs.buffer.Marker>.

(field array 'length) now works.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.64 to 1.6.66

Added documentation to the manual for Homogeneous numeric vector datatypes (SRFI-4).

You can now specify characters using their Unicode value: #\u05d0 is alef.

Kawa now uses a more mnemonic name mangling Scheme. For example, a Scheme function named <= would get compiled to method $Ls$Eq.

There is now working and useful module support, thought not all features are implemented. The basic idea is that a module can be any class that has a default constructor (or all of whose fields and methods are static); the public fields and methods of such a class are its exported definitions. Compiling a Scheme file produces such a module. Doing: (require <classname>) will create an anonymous instance of <classname> (if needed), and add all its exported definitions to the current environment. Note that if you import a class in a module you are compiling, then an instance of the module will be created at compile-time, and imported definitions are not re-imported. (For now you must compile a module, you cannot just load it.)

The define-private keyword creates a module-local definition.

New syntax to override some properties of the current module: (module-name <name>) overrides the default name for a module. (module-extends <class>) specifies the super-class. (module-implements <interface> ...) specfies the implemented interfaces.

The syntax: (require ’keyword) is syntactic sugar for (require <classname>) where the classname is find is a "module catalog" (currently hard-wired). This provides compatibility with Slib. The Slib "features" gen-write, pretty-print, pprint-file, and printf are now available in Kawa; more will be added, depending on time and demand. See the package directory gnu/kawa/slib for what is available.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.62 to 1.6.64

A lot of improvements to JEmacs (see JEmacs.SourceForge.net).

kawa-compiled-VERSION.zip is replaced by kawa-compiled-VERSION.jar.

You can now use Kawa to generate applets, using the new –applet switch, Check the "Applet compilation" section in the manual. Generating an application using the –main flag should work again. Neither –applet nor –main has Scheme hard-wired any more.

A new macro ‘(this)’ evaluates to the "this object" - the current instance of the current class. The current implementation is incomplete, and buggy, but it will have to do for now.

The command-line argument -f FILENAME will load the same files types as load.

When a source file is compiled, the top-level definitions (procedures, variables, and macros) are compiled to final fields on the resulting class. This are not automatically entered into the current environment; instead that is the responsibility of whoever loads the compiled class. This is a major step towards a module system for Kawa.

There is a new form define-private which is like define, except that the defined name is not exported from the current module.

A procedure that has optional arguments is now typically compiled into multiple methods. If it’s a top-level procedure, these will be methods in the modules "ModuleBody" class, with the same (mangled) name. The compiler can in many cases call the appropriate method directly. Usually, each method takes a fixed number of arguments, which means we save the overhead of creating an array for the arguments.

A top-level procedure declared using the form (define (NAME ARS ...) BODY ..) is assumed to be "constant" if it isn’t assigned to in the current compilation unit. A call in the same compilation unit will now be implemented as a direct method call. This is not done if the prcedure is declared with the form: (define NAME (lambda (ARGS ,,,) BODY ...)

gnu.expr.Declaration no longer inherits from gnu.bytecode.Variable.

A gnu.mapping.Environment now resolves hash index collisions using "double hashing" and "open addressing" instead of "chaining" through Binding. This allows a Binding to appear in multiple Environments.

The classes Sequence, Pair, PairWithPosition, FString, and Char were moved from kawa.lang to the new package gnu.kawa.util. It seems that these classes (except perhaps Char) belong together. The classes List and Vector were also moved, and at the same time renamed to LList and FVector, respectively, to avoid clashed with classes in java.util.

New data types and procedures for "uniform vectors" of primitive types were implemented. These follow the SRFI-4 specification, which you can find at http://srfi.schemers.org/srfi-4/srfi-4.html .

You can now use the syntax name :: type to specify the type of a parameter. For example: (define (vector-length x :: <vector>) (invoke x 'length)) The following also works: (define (vector-length (x :: <vector>)) ...).

(define-member-alias name object [fname]) is new syntactic sugar for (define-alias name (field object fname)), where the default for fname is the mangling of name.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.60 to 1.6.62

The new function ‘invoke’ allows you to call a Java method. All of ‘invoke’, ‘invoke-static’ and ‘make’ now select the bets method. They are also inlined at compile time in many cases. Specifically, if there is a method known to be definitely applicable, based on compile-time types of the argument expressions, the compiler will choose the most specific such method.

The functions slot-ref, slot-set!, field, and static-field are now inlined by the compiler when it can.

Added open-input-string, open-output-string, get-output-string from SRFI-6. See http://srfi.schemers.org/srfi-6/srfi-6.html.

The manual has a new section "Mapping Scheme names to Java names", and a new chapter "Types". The chapters "Extensions", "Objects and Classes", and "Low-level functions" have been extensivley re-organized.

The Kawa license has been simplified. There used to be two licenses: One for the packages gnu.*, and one for the packages kawa.*. There latter has been replaced by the former. The "License" section of the manual was also improved.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.59 to 1.6.60

There is a new package gnu.kawa.reflect. Some classes that used to be in kawa.lang or kawa.standard are now there.

The procedures slot-ref and slot-set! are now available. They are equivalent to the existing ‘field’, but reading a field ‘x’ will look for ‘getX’ method if there is no public ‘x’ field; writing to a field will look for ‘setX’.

The procedure ‘make’ makes it convenient to create new objects.

There is now a teaser screen snapshot of "JEmacs" at http://www.bothner.com/~per/papers/jemacs.png.

The html version of the manual now has a primitive index. The manual has been slightly re-organized, with a new "Classes and Objects" chapter.

The new functions invoke-static and class-methods allow you to call an arbitary Java method. They both take a class specification and a method name. The result of class-methods is a generic procedure consisting of those methods whose names match. (Instance methods are also matched; they are treated the asme as class methods with an extra initial argument.) The invoke-static function also takes extra arguments, and actually calls the "best"-matching method. An example:

        (invoke-static <java.lang.Thread> 'sleep 100)

Many fewer classes are now generated when compiling a Scheme file. It used to be that each top-level procedure got compiled to its own class; that is no longer the case. The change should lead to faster startup and less resource use, but procedure application will probably be noticably slower (though not so much slower as when reflection is used). The reason for the slowdown is that we in the general case now do an extra method call, plus a not-yet-optimized switch statement. This change is part of the new Kawa module system. That will allow the compiler to substitute direct methods calls in more cases, which I hope will more than make up for the slowdown.

A Scheme procedure is now in general compiled to a Java method whose name is a "mangling" of the Scheme procedure’s name. If the procedure takes a variable number of parameters, then "$V" is added to the name; this indicates that the last argument is a Java array containing the rest of the arguments. Conversely, calling a Java method whose name ends in "$V" passes any excess arguments in the last argument, which must be an array type.

Many changes to the "Emacs-emulation" library in gnu.jemacs.buffer: * Implemented commands to read and save files. * We ask for file and buffer names using a dialog pop-up window. * Split windows correctly, so that the windows that are not split keep their sizes, the windows being split gets split as specified, and the frame does not change size. Now also handles horizonal splits. * Fairly good support for buffer-local keymaps and Emacs-style keymap search order. A new class BufferKeymap manages the active keymaps of a buffer. Multi-key key-sequences are handled. Pending prefix keys are remembered on a per-buffer basis (whereas Emacs does it globally).

There is now some low-level support for generic procedures.

The R5RS primitives let-syntax and letrec-syntax for defining local syntax extensions (macros) should now work. Also define-syntax works as an internal definition. All of these should now be properly "hygienic". (There is one known exception: symbols listed among the literals lists are matched as raw symbols, rather that checking that the symbol has the same binding, if any, as at the defining site.) The plan is to support general functions as hygienic rewriters, as in the Chez Scheme "syntax-case" system; as one part of that plan, the syntax-case primitive is available, but so far without any of the supporting machinary to support hygiene.

The read-line procedure was added. This allows you to efficiently read a line from an input port. The interface is the same as scsh and Guile.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.58 to 1.6.59

define-alias now works both top-level and inside a function.

Optimized eqv? so if one of the arguments is constant and not Char or Numeric, inline it the same way eq? is. (This helps case when the labels are symbols, which help the "lattice" benchmark.) ???

The Emacs-related packages are now grouped under a new gnu.jemacs package.

Improved framework for catching errors. This means improved error messages when passing a parameter of the wrong type. Many standard procedures have been improved.

Simplified, documented, and tested (!) procedure for building Kawa from source under Windows (95/98/NT).

New macros trace and untrace for tracing procedures. After executing (trace PROCEDURE), debugging output will be written (to the standard error port) every time PROCEDURE is called, with the parameters and return value. Use (untrace PROCEDURE) to turn tracing off.

New utility functions (system-tmpdir) and (make-temporary-file [format]).

A new (unfinished) framework supports multiple languages. The command-line option –elisp selects Emacs Lisp, while –scheme (the default) selects Scheme. (The only difference so far is the reader syntax; that will change.)

The ‘format’ function now provides fairly complete functionality for CommonLisp-style formatting. (See the Comon Lisp hyperspec at http://www.harlequin.com/education/books/HyperSpec/Body/sec_22-3.html.) The floating point formatters (~F, ~E, ~G, ~$) now pass the formatst.scm test (from Slib, but with some "fixes"; in the testsuite directory). Also, output ports now track column numbers, so ~T and ~& also work correctly.

A new package gnu.emacs provides various building blocks for building an Emacs-like text editor. These classes are only compiled when Kawa is configured with the new –with-swing configuration option. This is a large initial step towards "JEmacs" - an Emacs re-implemented to use Kawa, Java, and Swing, but with full support (using gnu.elisp) for traditional Emacs Lisp. For more imformation see gnu/emacs/overview.html.

A new configuration option –with-swing can be used if Swing is available. It is currently only used in gnu.emacs, but that may change.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.56 to 1.6.58

Kawa is now "properly tail-recursive" if you invoke it with the –full-tail-calls flag. (Exception: the eval procedure does not perform proper tail calls, in violation of R5RS. This will be fixed in a future release.) Code compiled when –full-tail-calls is in effect is also properly tail-recursive. Procedures compiled with –full-tail-calls can call procedures compiled without it, and vice versa (but of course without doing proper tail calls). The default is still –no-full-tail-calls, partly because of performance concerns, partly because that provides better compatibility with Java conventions and tools.

The keywords let (including named let), let*, and letrec support type specifiers for the declared variables For example:

    (let ((lst :: <list> (foo x))) (reverse lst))

Square brackets [ ... ] are allowed as a synonym of parentheses ( ... ).

Changes from Kawa 1.6.55 to 1.6.57

A new command-line flag –server PORT specifies that Kawa should run as a telnet server on the specified PORT, creating a new read-eval-print loop for each connection. This allows you to connect using any telnet client program to a remote "Kawa server".

A new front-end program, written in C, that provides editing of input lines, using the GNU readline library. This is a friendlier interface than the plain "java kawa.repl". However, because kawa.c needs readline and suitable networking library support, it is not built by default, but only when you configure Kawa with the –enable-kawa-frontend flag.

The way Scheme names are mapped ("mangled") into Java identifiers is now more natural. E.g. "foo-bar?" now is mapped to "isFooBar".

New syntax (object (SUPERS ...) FIELD-AND-METHODS ...) for creating a new object instance of an anonymous class. Now fairly powerful.

New procedures field and static-field for more convenient field access.

Syntactic sugar: (lambda args <type> body) -> (lambda args (as <type> body)). This is especially useful for declaring methods in classes.

A new synchonized form allows you to synchronize on an arbitrary Java object, and execute some forms while having an exclusive lock on the object. (The syntax matches that used by Skij.)

Changes from Kawa 1.6.53 to 1.6.55

New –debug-dump-zip option writes out a .zip file for compilation. (Useful for debugging Kawa.)

You can now declare parameter types.

Lot of work on more efficient procedure representation and calling convention: Inlining, directly callable statics method, plus some procedures no longer generate a separate Class.

Local functions that are only called from one locations, except for tail-recursion, are now inlined. This inlines do loops, and most "named let" loops.

New representation of closures (closures with captured local variables). We no longer use an array for the closure. Instead we store the captured variables in the Procedure itself. This should be faster (since we can use field accesses rather than array indexing, which requires bounds checking), and avoids a separate environment object.

If the compiler sees a function call whose (non-lexically-bound) name matches an existing (globally-defined) procedure, and that procedure instance has a static method named either "apply" or the mangled procedure name, them the compiler emits a direct call to that method. This can make a very noticable speed difference, though it may violate strict Scheme sementics, and some code may break.

Partial support for first-class "location" variables.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.53 to 1.6.54

Created new packages gnu.mapping and gnu.expr. Many classes were moved from kawa.lang to the new packages. (This is part of the long-term process of splitting Kawa into more manageable chunks, separating the Scheme-specific code from the language-independent code, and moving classes under the gnu hierarchy.)

You can now write keywords with the colon first (e.g. :KEYWORD), which has exactly the same effect and meaning as putting the colon last (e.g. KEYWORD:). The latter is preferred is being more consistent with normal English use of punctuation, but the former is allowed for compatibility with soem other Scheme implementations and Common Lisp.

Changes from Kawa 1.6.52 to 1.6.53

The new package gnu.text contains facilities for reading, formatting, and manipulating text. Some classes in kawa.lang where moved to there.

Added string-upcase!, string-downcase!, string-capitalize!, string-upcase, string-downcase, and string-capitalize; compatible with Slib.

Character constants can now use octal notation (as in Guile). Writing a character uses octal format when that seems best.

A format function, similar to that in Common Lisp (and Slib) has been added.

The default parameter of a #!optional or #!key parameter can now be #!null.

Changes since Kawa 1.6.51

The "record" feature has been changed to that a "record-type descriptor" is now a gnu.bytecode.ClassType (a <record-type>), rather than a java.lang.Class. Thus make-record-type now returns a <record-typee>, not a Class, and record-type-descriptor takes a <record-typee>, not a Class.

More robust Eval interfaces.

New Lexer abstract class. New ScmRead class (which extends Lexer) now contains the Scheme reader (moved from Inport). Now read errors are kept in queue, and can be recovered from.

Comparing an exact rational and an inexact real (double) is now done as if by first converting the double to exact, to satisfy R5RS.

Changes since Kawa 1.6.1

The compile virtual method in Expression now takes a Target object, representing the "destination". The special ConditionalTarget is used to evaluate the test of an ’if expression. This allows us to generate much better code for and, or, eq?, not and nested if inside an if.

Added port-line, port-column, and set-port-line! to match Guile.

The Makefiles have been written so all out-of-date .java (or .scm). files in a directory are compiled using a single invocation of javac (or kawa). Building Kawa should now be much faster. (But note that this depends on unreleased recent autoamke changes.)

How the Kawa version number is compiled into Kawa was changed to make it easier for people who want to build from source on non-Unix-like systems.

A new gnu.ecmascript package contains an extremely incomplete implementation of ECMSScript, the ECMA standardized version of JavaScript. It includes an ECMAScript lexer (basically complete), parser (the framework is there but most of the language is missing), incomplete expression evaluation, and a read-eval-print-loop (for testing only).

Changes in Kawa 1.6.1

Improved Kawa home page with extra links, pointer to Java-generated api docs, and homepages for gnu.math and gnu.bytecode.

Implemented system, make-process, and some related procedures.

Added macros for primitive access to object fields, static fields, and Java arrays. Added constant-fold syntax, and used it for the other macros.

The –main flag compiles Scheme code to an application (containing a main method), which can be be invoked directly by a Java interpreter.

Implemented –version (following GNU standards) as kawa.repl command-line flag.

Changes since Kawa 1.5.93

Adding make procedure to create new objects/records.

Extended (set! (f . args) value) to be equivalent to ((setter f) value . args). Implemented setter, as well as (setter car) and (setter cdr).

Can now get and set a record field value using an application: (rec ’fname) gets the value of the field named fname in record rec. (set! (rec ’fname) value) sets the value of the field named fname in rec.

A partial re-write of the implementation of input ports and the Scheme reader, to fix some problems, add some features, and improve performance.

Compiled .class files are now installed in $(datadir)/java, rather than $(prefix)/java. By default, that means they are installed in /usr/local/shared/java, rather than /usr/local/java.

There is now internal infrastructure to support inlining of procedures, and general procedure-specific optimized code generation.

There is better testing that the right number of arguments are passed to a procedure, and better error messages when you don’t. If the procedure is inlined, you get a compile-time error message.

The functions created by primitive-constructor, primitive-virtual-method, primitive-static-method, and primitive-interface-method are now first-class procedure values. They use the Java reflection facily, except when the compiler can directly inline them (in which case it generates the same efficient bytecodes as before).

New functions instance? (tests type membership) and as (converts).

The kawa.html is now split into several files, one per chapter. The table of contents is now kawa_toc.html.

The syntactic form try-catch provides low-level exception handler support. It is basically the same as Java’s try/catch form, but in Scheme syntax. The new procedure primitive-throw throws an exception object.

The higher-level catch and throw procedures implement exception handling where the handler is specified with a "key" (a symbol). These functions were taken from Guile.

The error function has been generalized to take multiple arguments (as in Guile). It is now a wrapper around (throw ’misc-error ...).

There is a new "friendly" GUI access to the Kawa command-line. If you invoke kawa.repl with the -w flag, a new interaction window is created. This is uses the AWT TextArea class. You can create multiple "consoles". They can either share top-level enevironments, or have separate environments. This window interface has some nice features, including editing. Added a scheme-window procedure, which is another way to create a window.

Changes since Kawa 1.5

The default prompt now shows continuations lines differently.

The copy-file function was added.

The variable port-char-encoding controls how external files are converted to/from internal Unicode characters. It also controls whether CR and CR-LF are converted to LF.

The reader by default no longer down-cases letters in symbols. A new variable symbol-read-case control how case is handled: ’P (the default) preserves case; ’U upper-cases letters; ’D or -" down-cases letters; and ’I inverts case.

The gnu.bytecode package now supports exception handlers. The new syntactic form try-finally supports a cleanup hook that is run after some other code finishes (normally or abnormally). Try-finally is used to implement dynamic-wind and fluid-let.

The environment handling has been improved to support thread-specific environments, a thread-safe fluid-let, and multiple top-levels. (The latter still needs a bit of work.)

The gnu.bytecode package has been extensively changed. There are new classes representing the various standard Attributes, and data associated with an attribute is now stored there.

Added new procedures environment-bound? and scheme-implementation-version.

Scheme symbols are represented as java.lang.String objects. Interned symbols are interned Strings; uninterned symbols are uninterned Strings. Note that Java strings literals are automatically interned in JDK 1.1. This change makes symbols slightly more efficient, and moves Kawa closer to Java.

Ports now use the JDK 1.1 character-based Reader and Writer classes, rather than the byte-oriented InputStream and OutputStream classes. This supports different reading and writing different character encodings [in theory - there is no support yet for other than Ascii or binary files].

An interactive input port now has a prompt function associated with it. It is settable with set-input-port-prompter!. The prompt function takes one argument (the input port), and returns a prompt string. There are also user functions for inquiring about the current line and column number of an input port.

The R4RS procedures transcript-on and transcript-off are implemented.

Standard types can be referred to using syntax similar to RScheme. For example Scheme strings now have the type <string> which is preferred to "kawa.lang.FString" (which in addition to being longer, is also more suspectible to changes in internal implementation). Though these types are first-class values, this is so far mainly useful for invoking primitive methods.

Changes from Kawa 1.4 to 1.5

Execute a ~/.kawarc.scm file on startup, if it exists.

Add a number of functions for testing, renaming, and deleting files. These are meant to be compatible with scsh, Guile, and MIT Scheme: file-exists?, file-directory?, file-readable?, file-writable?, delete-file, rename-file, create-diretory, and the variable home-directory.

Fixed some small bugs, mainly in gnu.math and in load.

Generalize apply to accept an arbitrary Sequence, or a primitive Java array.

Changes from Kawa 1.2 to 1.4

The codegen package has been renamed gnu.bytecode. The kawa.math package has been moved to gnu.math. Both packages have new license: No restrictions if you use an unmodified release, but GNU General Public License. Let me know if that causes problems. The rest of Kawa still has the old license.

Implement defmacro and gentemp.

Implement make-record-type and related functions to create and use new record types. A record type is implemented as a java.lang.Class object, and this feature depends on the new reflection features of JDK 1.1.

Implement keywords, and extend lambda parameter lists to support #!optional #!rest and #!keyword parameters (following DSSSL).

Added more primitives to call arbitrary interface and constructor methods.

Changes from Kawa 1.0 to 1.2

Added primitives to make it easy to call arbitrary Java methods from Scheme.

Exact rational arithetic is now fully implemented. All integer functions now believed to correctly handle bignums. Logical operations on exact integers have been implemented. These include all the logical functions from Guile.

Complex numbers are implemented (except {,a}{sin,cos,tan}). Quantities (with units) are implemented (as in DSSSL).

Eval is available, as specified for R5RS. Also implemented are scheme-report-environment, null-environment, and interaction-environment.

Internal define is implemented.

Rough support for multiple threads is implemented.

Moved kawa class to kawa/repl. Merged in kawac (compiler) functionality. A ’kawa’ shell-script is now created. This is now the preferred interface to both the interactive evaluator and the compiler (on Unix-like systems).

Now builds "without a snag" using Cafe 1.51 under Win95. (Symantec JIT (ver 2.00b19) requires disabling JIT - JAVA_COMPCMD=disable.) Compiles under JDK 1.1 beta (with some warnings).

A testsuite (and testing framework) was added.

Documentation moved to doc directory. There is now an internals overview, in doc/kawa-tour.ps.

Changes since 0.4

The numeric classes have been re-written. There is partial support for bignums (infinite-precision integers), but divide (for example) has not been implemented yet. The representation of bignums uses 2’s complement, where the "big digits" are laid out so as to be compatible with the mpn functions of the GNU Multi-Precision library (gmp). (The intent is that a future version of Kawa will support an option to use gmp native functions for speed.)

The kawa application takes a number of useful command-line switches.

Basically all of R4RS has been implemented. All the essential forms and functions are implemented. Almost all of the optional forms are implemented. The exceptions are transcript-on, transcript-off, and the functions for complex numbers, and fractions (exact non-integer rationals).

Loading a source file with load now wraps the entire file in a lambda (named "atFileLevel"). This is for better error reporting, and consistency with compile-file.

Changes since 0.3

The hygienic macros described in the appendix to R4RS are now impemented (but only the define-syntax form). They are used to implement the standard "do" form.

The R5RS multiple value functions values and call-with-values are implemented.

Macros (and primitive syntax) can now be autoloaded as well as procedures.

New kawac application compiles to one or more .class files.

Compile time errors include line numbers. Uncaught exceptions cause a stack trace that includes .scm line numbers. This makes it more practical to debug Kawa with a Java debugger.

Quasiquotation is implemented.

Various minor bug fixes and optimizations.

Changes since 0.2

The biggest single change is that Scheme procedures are now compiled to Java bytecodes. This is mainly for efficiency, but it also allows us to do tail-recursion-elimination in some cases.

The "codegen" library is included. This is a toolkit that handles most of the details needed to generate Java bytecode (.class) files.

The internal structure of Kawa has been extensively re-written, especially how syntax transforms, eval, and apply are done, largely due to the needs for compilation.

Almost all the R4RS procedures are now implemented, except that there are still large gaps in Section 6.5 "Numbers".

Up: The Kawa Scheme language

Previous: The Kawa Scheme language

Next: Features

Numerical input and output

Procedure: number->string z [radix]

The procedure number->string takes a number and a radix and returns as a string an external representation of the given number in the given radix such that

(let ((number number)
      (radix radix))
  (eqv? number
        (string->number (number->string number radix)
                        radix)))

is true. It is an error if no possible result makes this expression true.

If present, radix must be an exact integer in the range 2 to 36, inclusive. If omitted, radix defaults to 10.

If z is inexact, the radix is 10, and the above expression can be satisfied by a result that contains a decimal point, then the result contains a decimal point and is expressed using the minimum number of digits (exclusive of exponent and trailing zeroes) needed to make the above expression; otherwise the format of the result is unspecified.

The result returned by number->string never contains an explicit radix prefix.

Note: The error case can occur only when z is not a complex number or is a complex number with a non-rational real or imaginary part.

Rationale: If z is an inexact number and the radix is 10, then the above expression is normally satisfied by a result containing a decimal point. The unspecified case allows for infinities, NaNs, and unusual representations.

Procedure: string->number string [radix]

Returns a number of the maximally precise representation expressed by the given string. It is an error if radix is not an exact integer in the range 2 to 26, inclusive.

If supplied, radix is a default radix that will be overridden if an explicit radix prefix is present in the string (e.g. "#o177"). If radix is not supplied, then the default radix is 10. If string is not a syntactically valid notation for a number, or would result in a number that the implementation cannot represent, then string->number returns #f. An error is never signaled due to the content of string.

(string->number "100")      ⇒  100
(string->number "100" 16)   ⇒  256
(string->number "1e2")      ⇒  100.0
(string->number "#x100" 10) ⇒  256

Up: Quantities and Numbers

Previous: Arithmetic operations

Next: Quaternions

Parameter objects

A parameter object is a procedure that is bound to a location, and may optionally have a conversion procedure. The procedure accepts zero or one argument. When the procedure is called with zero arguments, the content of the location is returned. On a call with one argument the content of the location is updated with the result of applying the parameter object’s conversion procedure to the argument.

Parameter objects are created with the make-parameter procedure which takes one or two arguments. The second argument is a one argument conversion procedure. If only one argument is passed to make-parameter the identity function is used as a conversion procedure. A new location is created and asociated with the parameter object. The initial content of the location is the result of applying the conversion procedure to the first argument of make-parameter.

Note that the conversion procedure can be used for guaranteeing the type of the parameter object’s binding and/or to perform some conversion of the value.

The parameterize special form, when given a parameter object and a value, binds the parameter object to a new location for the dynamic extent of its body. The initial content of the location is the result of applying the parameter object’s conversion procedure to the value. The parameterize special form behaves analogously to let when binding more than one parameter object (that is the order of evaluation is unspecified and the new bindings are only visible in the body of the parameterize special form).

When a new thread is created using future or runnable then the child thread inherits initial values from its parent. Once the child is running, changing the value in the child does not affect the value in the parent or vice versa. (In the past this was not the case: The child would share a location with the parent except within a parameterize. This was changed to avoid unsafe and inefficient coupling between threads.)

Note that parameterize and fluid-let have similar binding and sharing behavior. The difference is that fluid-let modifies locations accessed by name, while make-parameter and parameterize create anonymous locations accessed by calling a parameter procedure.

The R5RS procedures current-input-port and current-output-port are parameter objects.

Procedure: make-parameter init [converter]

Returns a new parameter object which is bound in the global dynamic environment to a location containing the value returned by the call (converter init). If the conversion procedure converter is not specified the identity function is used instead.

The parameter object is a procedure which accepts zero or one argument. When it is called with no argument, the content of the location bound to this parameter object in the current dynamic environment is returned. When it is called with one argument, the content of the location is set to the result of the call (converter arg), where arg is the argument passed to the parameter object, and an unspecified value is returned.

(define radix
  (make-parameter 10))

(define write-shared
  (make-parameter
    #f
    (lambda (x)
      (if (boolean? x)
          x
          (error "only booleans are accepted by write-shared")))))

(radix)           ⇒  10
(radix 2)
(radix)           ⇒  2
(write-shared 0)  gives an error

(define prompt
  (make-parameter
    123
    (lambda (x)
      (if (string? x)
          x
          (with-output-to-string (lambda () (write x)))))))

(prompt)       ⇒  "123"
(prompt ">")
(prompt)       ⇒  ">"

Syntax: parameterize ((expr1 expr2) ...) body

The expressions expr1 and expr2 are evaluated in an unspecified order. The value of the expr1 expressions must be parameter objects. For each expr1 expression and in an unspecified order, the local dynamic environment is extended with a binding of the parameter object expr1 to a new location whose content is the result of the call (converter val), where val is the value of expr2 and converter is the conversion procedure of the parameter object. The resulting dynamic environment is then used for the evaluation of body (which refers to the R5RS grammar nonterminal of that name). The result(s) of the parameterize form are the result(s) of the body.

(radix)                                              ⇒  2
(parameterize ((radix 16)) (radix))                  ⇒  16
(radix)                                              ⇒  2

(define (f n) (number->string n (radix)))

(f 10)                                               ⇒  "1010"
(parameterize ((radix 8)) (f 10))                    ⇒  "12"
(parameterize ((radix 8) (prompt (f 10))) (prompt))  ⇒  "1010"

Up: Eval and Environments

Previous: Locations

Performance of numeric operations

Kawa can generally do a pretty good job of generating efficient code for numeric operations, at least when it knows or can figure out the types of the operands.

The basic operations +, -, and * are compiled to single-instruction bytecode if both operands are int or long. Likewise, if both operands are floating-point (or one is floating-point and the other is rational), then single-instruction double or float instructions are emitted.

A binary operation involving an infinite-precision integer and a fixed-size int or long is normally evaluated by expanding the latter to integer and using integer arithmetic. An exception is an integer literal whose value fits in an int or long - in that case the operation is done using int or long arithmetic.

In general, integer literals have amorphous type. When used to infer the type of a variable, they have integer type:

(let ((v1 0))
  ... v1 has type integer ... )

However, a literal whose value fits in the int or long range is implicitly viewed int or long in certain contexts, primarily method overload resolution and binary arithmetic (as mentioned above).

The comparison functions <, <=, =, >, and => are also optimized to single instriction operations if the operands have appropriate type. However, the functions zero?, positive?, and negative? have not yet been optimized. Instead of (positive? x) write (> x 0).

There are a number of integer division and modulo operations. If the operands are int or long, it is faster to use quotient and remainder rather than div and mod (or modulo). If you know the first operand is non-negative and the second is positive, then use quotient and remainder. (If an operand is an arbitrary-precision integer, then it dosn’t really matter.)

The logical operations bitwise-and, bitwise-ior, bitwise-xor, bitwise-not, bitwise-arithmetic-shift-left, bitwise-arithmetic-shift-right are compiled to single bitcode instructions if the operands are int or long. Avoid bitwise-arithmetic-shift if the sign of the shift is known. If the operands are arbitrary-precision integer, a library call is needed, but run-time type dispatch is avoided.

Up: Quantities and Numbers

Previous: Logical Number Operations

Projects using Kawa

MIT App Inventor for Android (formerly Google App Inventor) uses Kawa to translate its visual blocks language.

The HypeDyn hypertext fiction authoring tool is written in Kawa. HypeDyn (pronounced "hyped in") is a procedural hypertext fiction authoring tool for people who want to create text-based interactive stories that adapt to reader choice. HypeDyn is free to download and open source, and runs on Linux, MacOS and Windows. This is a research project carried out at the Department of Communications and New Media, National University of Singapore.

Nü Echo develops high-performance speech enabled applications. Nü Echo uses Kawa for the development of innovative speech application development tools, like a complete grammar IDE.

Merced Systems, Inc. uses Kawa extensively in their contact center performance management product Merced Peformance Suite. Kawa Scheme is used for all development and has allowed Merced to realize the large productivity gains that come with using Scheme while still maintaining tight integration with a large number of Java libraries.

JEmacs is included in the Kawa distribution. It is a project to re-implement Emacs, allowing a mix of Java, Scheme, and Emacs Lisp. It has its own home-page.

BRL (“the Beautiful Report Language") is a database-oriented language to embed in HTML and other markup. BRL allows you to embed Scheme in an HTML file on a web server.

The SchemeWay Project is a set of Eclipse plug-ins for professional Scheme programming. The first plugin released, SchemeScript, is a fully-featured Scheme editor customizable in Scheme. It embeds the Kawa Scheme system and has many features that ease Kawa Scheme programming (like code completion on variable names, class and method names, namespaces, etc).

The Health Media Research Laboratory, part of the Comprehensive Cancer Center at the University of Michigan, is using Kawa as an integral part of its core tailoring technologies. Java programs using Kawa libraries are used to administer customized web-based surveys, generate tailored feedback, validate data, and "characterize," or transform, data. Kawa code is embedded directly in XML-formatted surveys and data dictionaries. Performance and ease of implementation has far exceeded expectations. For more information contact Paul R. Potts, Technical Director, Health Media Research Lab, <potts@umich.edu>.

Mike Dillon (mdillon@gjt.org) did the preliminary work of creating a Kawa plugin for jEdit. It is called SchemeShell and provides a REPL inside of the jEdit console for executing expressions in Kawa (much as the BeanShell plugin does with the BeanShell scripting language). It is currently available only via CVS from:

CVSROOT=:pserver:anonymous@cvs.jedit.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/jedit
MODULE=plugins/SchemeShell

STMicroelectronics (marco.vezzoli@st.com) uses Kawa in a prototypal intranet 3tier information retrieval system as a communication protocol between server and clients, and to do server agents programming.

Up: The Kawa Community

Previous: Technical Support for Kawa

Next: Ideas and tasks for contributing to Kawa

Regular expressions

Kawa provides regular expressions, which is a convenient mechanism for matching a string against a pattern and maybe replacing matching parts.

A regexp is a string that describes a pattern. A regexp matcher tries to match this pattern against (a portion of) another string, which we will call the text string. The text string is treated as raw text and not as a pattern.

Most of the characters in a regexp pattern are meant to match occurrences of themselves in the text string. Thus, the pattern “abc” matches a string that contains the characters “a”, “b”, “c” in succession.

In the regexp pattern, some characters act as metacharacters, and some character sequences act as metasequences. That is, they specify something other than their literal selves. For example, in the pattern “a.c”, the characters “a” and “c” do stand for themselves but the metacharacter “.” can match any character (other than newline). Therefore, the pattern “a.c” matches an “a”, followed by any character, followed by a “c”.

If we needed to match the character “.” itself, we escape it, ie, precede it with a backslash “\”. The character sequence “\.” is thus a metasequence, since it doesn’t match itself but rather just “.”. So, to match “a” followed by a literal “.” followed by “c” we use the regexp pattern “a\.c”. To write this as a Scheme string literal, you need to quote the backslash, so you need to write "a\\.c". Kawa also allows the literal syntax #/a\.c/, which avoids the need to double the backslashes.

You can choose between two similar styles of regular expressions. The two differ slightly in terms of which characters act as metacharacters, and what those metacharacters mean:

Functions starting with regex- are implemented using the java.util.regex package. This is likely to be more efficient, has better Unicode support and some other minor extra features, and literal syntax #/a\.c/ mentioned above.

Functions starting with pregexp- are implemented in pure Scheme using Dorai Sitaram’s “Portable Regular Expressions for Scheme” library. These will be portable to more Scheme implementations, including BRL, and is available on older Java versions.

Java regular expressions

The syntax for regular expressions is documented here.

Type: regex

A compiled regular expression, implemented as java.util.regex.Pattern.

Constructor: regex arg

Given a regular expression pattern (as a string), compiles it to a regex object.

(regex "a\\.c")

This compiles into a pattern that matches an “a”, followed by any character, followed by a “c”.

The Scheme reader recognizes “#/” as the start of a regular expression pattern literal, which ends with the next un-escaped “/”. This has the big advantage that you don’t need to double the backslashes:

#/a\.c/

This is equivalent to (regex "a\\.c"), except it is compiled at read-time. If you need a literal “/” in a pattern, just escape it with a backslash: “#/a\/c/” matches a “a”, followed by a “/”, followed by a “c”.

You can add single-letter modifiers following the pattern literal. The following modifiers are allowed:

i

The modifier “i” cause the matching to ignore case. For example the following pattern matches “a” or “A”.

#/a/i

m

Enables “metaline” mode. Normally metacharacters “^” and “$’ match at the start end end of the entire input string. In metaline mode “^” and “$” also match just before or after a line terminator.

Multiline mode can also be enabled by the metasequence “(?m)”.

s

Enable “singleline” (aka “dot-all”) mode. In this mode the matacharacter “. matches any character, including a line breaks. This mode be enabled by the metasequence “(?s)”.

The following functions accept a regex either as a pattern string or a compiled regex pattern. I.e. the following are all equivalent:

(regex-match "b\\.c" "ab.cd")
(regex-match #/b\.c/ "ab.cd")
(regex-match (regex "b\\.c") "ab.cd")
(regex-match (java.util.regex.Pattern:compile "b\\.c") "ab.cd")

These all evaluate to the list ("b.c").

The following functions must be imported by doing one of:

(require 'regex) ;; or
(import (kawa regex))

Procedure: regex-match-positions regex string [start [end]]

The procedure regex‑match‑position takes pattern and a text string, and returns a match if the regex matches (some part of) the text string.

Returns #f if the regexp did not match the string; and a list of index pairs if it did match.

(regex-match-positions "brain" "bird") ⇒ #f
(regex-match-positions "needle" "hay needle stack")
  ⇒ ((4 . 10))

In the second example, the integers 4 and 10 identify the substring that was matched. 4 is the starting (inclusive) index and 10 the ending (exclusive) index of the matching substring.

(substring "hay needle stack" 4 10) ⇒ "needle"

In this case the return list contains only one index pair, and that pair represents the entire substring matched by the regexp. When we discuss subpatterns later, we will see how a single match operation can yield a list of submatches.

regex‑match‑positions takes optional third and fourth arguments that specify the indices of the text string within which the matching should take place.

(regex-match-positions "needle"
  "his hay needle stack -- my hay needle stack -- her hay needle stack"
  24 43)
  ⇒ ((31 . 37))

Note that the returned indices are still reckoned relative to the full text string.

Procedure: regex-match regex string [start [end]]

The procedure regex‑match is called like regex‑match‑positions but instead of returning index pairs it returns the matching substrings:

(regex-match "brain" "bird") ⇒ #f
(regex-match "needle" "hay needle stack")
  ⇒ ("needle")

regex‑match also takes optional third and fourth arguments, with the same meaning as does regex‑match‑positions.

Procedure: regex-split regex string

Takes two arguments, a regex pattern and a text string, and returns a list of substrings of the text string, where the pattern identifies the delimiter separating the substrings.

(regex-split ":" "/bin:/usr/bin:/usr/bin/X11:/usr/local/bin")
  ⇒ ("/bin" "/usr/bin" "/usr/bin/X11" "/usr/local/bin")

(regex-split " " "pea soup")
  ⇒ ("pea" "soup")

If the first argument can match an empty string, then the list of all the single-character substrings is returned, plus we get a empty strings at each end.

(regex-split "" "smithereens")
  ⇒ ("" "s" "m" "i" "t" "h" "e" "r" "e" "e" "n" "s" "")

(Note: This behavior is different from pregexp-split.)

To identify one-or-more spaces as the delimiter, take care to use the regexp “ +”, not “ *”.

(regex-split " +" "split pea     soup")
  ⇒ ("split" "pea" "soup")
(regex-split " *" "split pea     soup")
  ⇒ ("" "s" "p" "l" "i" "t" "" "p" "e" "a" "" "s" "o" "u" "p" "")

Procedure: regex‑replace regex string replacement

Replaces the matched portion of the text string by another a replacdement string.

(regex-replace "te" "liberte" "ty")
  ⇒ "liberty"

Submatches can be used in the replacement string argument. The replacement string can use “$n” as a backreference to refer back to the nth submatch, ie, the substring that matched the nth subpattern. “$0” refers to the entire match.

(regex-replace #/_(.+?)_/
               "the _nina_, the _pinta_, and the _santa maria_"
		"*$1*"))
  ⇒ "the *nina*, the _pinta_, and the _santa maria_"

Procedure: regex‑replace* regex string replacement

Replaces all matches in the text string by the replacement string:

(regex-replace* "te" "liberte egalite fraternite" "ty")
  ⇒ "liberty egality fratyrnity"
(regex-replace* #/_(.+?)_/
                "the _nina_, the _pinta_, and the _santa maria_"
                "*$1*")
  ⇒ "the *nina*, the *pinta*, and the *santa maria*"

Procedure: regex-quote pattern

Takes an arbitrary string and returns a pattern string that precisely matches it. In particular, characters in the input string that could serve as regex metacharacters are escaped as needed.

(regex-quote "cons")
  ⇒ "\Qcons\E"

regex‑quote is useful when building a composite regex from a mix of regex strings and verbatim strings.

Portable Scheme regular expressions

This provides the procedures pregexp, pregexp‑match‑positions, pregexp‑match, pregexp‑split, pregexp‑replace, pregexp‑replace*, and pregexp‑quote.

Before using them, you must require them:

(require 'pregexp)

These procedures have the same interface as the corresponding regex- versions, but take slightly different pattern syntax. The replace commands use “\” instead of “$” to indicate substitutions. Also, pregexp‑split behaves differently from regex‑split if the pattern can match an empty string.

See here for details.

Java regular expressions
Portable Scheme regular expressions

Up: Characters and text

Previous: Unicode character classes and conversions

The REPL (read-eval-print-loop) console

The read-eval-print-loop (REPL) console is a convenient way to do simple programming, test out things, and experiment. As the name implies, the REPL repeatedly (in a loop) prints out a prompt, reads an input command, evaluates it, then prints the result.

The REPL is started when you invoke the kawa command with no arguments. For example:

$ kawa
#|kawa:1|# (define pi (* 2 (asin 1)))
#|kawa:2|# (list pi (sqrt pi))
(3.141592653589793 1.7724538509055159)
#|kawa:3|# 

The colors and styles used for the prompt and the user input depend on user preference and the capabilities of the console device. (If you read this on a color screen you should see pale green for the prompt and pale yellow for the user input; this matches the defaults for the DomTerm console.)

You can change the prompt string if you want. The default format depends on the (programming) language used; the one shown above is used for Scheme. It has the form of a comment, which can be convenient for copying and pasting lines.

You can change the output formatting with the --output-format command-line option.

The basic console has few frills, but should work in any enviroment where you have a console or terminal. It has no dependencies, except the kawa .jar file (and Java):

$ java kawa-2.92_invoke.jar
#|kawa:2|# 

On rare occason you may need to specify the --console flag.

Input line editing and history

When typing a command in a console it is helpful to go back and correct mistakes, repeat and edit previous commands, and so on. How well you can do this varies a lot depending on which tools you use. Kawa delegates input editing to an external tool. The recommended and default input-editing tool is the JLine3 library, which is bundled with the Kawa binary distribution.

JLine3 handles the normal editing comands, including arrow keys for moving around in the input, and deleting with backspace or delete. In general, JLine3 uses the same keybindings as GNU readline, which are based on Emacs key-bindings.

You can use the up-arrow to move to previous commands in the input history and down-arrow to go forwards. Control-R (“reverse search” searches backwards in the history for a previous command that contains the search string.

Multi-line commands are treated as a unit by JLine3: If Kawa determines that input is “incomplete” it will ask for continuation lines - and you can go back and edit previous lines in the same command. You can explicitly create a multi-line command with Escape-Space. An entry in the command history may be multiple lines.

Tab-completion works for Kawa-Scheme identifiers: If you type TAB after an identifier, Kawa will present a list of possible completions.

There are multiple alternatives to using JLine3. You can use GNU readline (if you configured with --enable-kawa-frontend). You can use a front-end program like rlfe or fep. You can use Emacs shell or scheme mode. You can also use DomTerm in line-edit mode, where the browser handles the editing.

console:use-jline=[yes|no]

Disable (with no) or enable (with yes, which is the default) input line editing with JLine.

console:console:jline-mouse=[yes|no]

Enable (with yes) mouse click reporting from most xterm-like terminals to JLine, which means you can move the input cursor with the mouse. This is disabled by default because it conflicts with other useful mouse actions (text selection using drag; middle-button paste; right-button context menu; and wheel mouse scrolling). If you enable mouse-reporting, on most terminals you can get the standard behavior when pressing the shift key. E.g. to enable selection, drag with the shift key pressed. (However, mouse-wheel scrolling may not work even with shift pressed.)

Running a Command Interpreter in a new Window

Instead of using an existing terminal window for Kawa’s REPL console, you can request a new window. The command-line options -w creates a new window. Kawa also creates a new window when it needs to create a REPL (for example if invoked with no options) and it is not running in a console.

You have a number of options for how the window appears and what it supports, controlled by text following -w. All except -wswing (and -wconsole) use DomTerm, so they depend on some kind of web browser technology. All except -wswing by default use JLine3 input editing, if available.

-w

Pick the default/preferred console implementation. You can specify your preference with the console:type= option, which is followed by one of the options below (without the "-w" prefix), It can also be list of options separated by semi-colons, in which case they are tried in order.

The current default (it may change) is as if you specified:

console:type="google-chrome;browser;javafx;swing;console"

-wbrowser

Creates a Kawa window or tab in your preferred desktop browser. Kawa starts a builtin HTTP and WebSocket server to communicate with the browser.

-wbrowser=command

Uses command to display the Kawa REPL. The command should include the pattern %U, which Kawa replaces with a URL that it listens to. (Alternatively, it can use the pattern %W, which Kawa replaces with the port number of its WebSocket server. However, this feature may be removed.) If the is no % in the command, Kawa add " %U". Thus -wbrowser=firefox is the same as -wbrowser="firefox %U".

-wgoogle-chrome

Creates a new Google Chrome window in “app mode” - i.e. with no location or menu bar. This is the same as -wbrowser="google-chrome --app=%U".

-wqtdomterm

Uses the QtDomTerm application. Same as -wbrowser="qtdomterm --connect localhost:%W", where %W is the port of the WebSocke server that Kawa starts.

-wjavafx

Creates a new window using JavaFX WebView, which runs in the same JVM as Kawa. While this doesn’t currently have much in the way of Kawa-specific menus or other features, it has the most potential for adding them in the future. However, it does require JavaFX, which is not always available, and which does not see a lot of love from Oracle. (It uses an old version of WebKit.)

-wswing

Create a console using the Swing toolkit. This is the old implementation of -w. It is deprecated because it only supports the builtin Swing line editing. (I.e. neither DomTerm or JLine3 features are available, though “printing” pictures does work.)

-wserve
-wserve=port

Starts up an HTTP server (along with a WebSocket server), but does not automatically create any browser windows. Instead you can use any modern browser to load http://localhost:port/. If port is not specified, the systems selects it (and prints it out).

-wconsole

Same as "--" - i.e. it uses the existing console.

console:type=preference-list

Specify the behavior of plain -w.

Using DomTerm

DomTerm is a family of terminal emulators that use the DomTerm JavaScript library.

You can either have Kawa start DomTerm:

$ kawa options -w

or start a DomTerm terminal emulator and have it start Kawa:

$ domterm kawa options --

(You can also start a shell in a domterm window, and then start kawa.)

Either approach works and both give you the benefits of DomTerm:

A xterm/ansi-compatible terminal emulator, which means you can use (for example) JLine3 for input editing.

You can “print” images, pictures, or HTML elements.

Pretty-printing is handled by the terminal, which means line-breaking is re-computed when window width changes.

Hide/show buttons allow you to temporarily hide/unhide the output from a specific command.

You can save a session as an HTML file, which can be viewed later. (Still with dynamic line-breaking and pretty-printing, as well as working hide/show buttons.) The file is actually XHTML, so it can be processed with XML-reading tools.

Distinct styles for prompts, input, error output and regular output, which can be customized with CSS.

For now it is recommended to use both DomTerm and JLine3.

Procedure: domterm-load-stylesheet stylesheet [name]

The string stylesheet should be a literal CSS stylesheet which is downloaded into the current DomTerm console. The new stylesheet is given the attribute name=name, where name defaults to "Kawa". If there is an existing stylesheey whose name attribute is name, it is replaced. In this example we change the background color to light gray:

(domterm-load-stylesheet "div.domterm { background-color: lightgray}")

Input line editing and history
Running a Command Interpreter in a new Window
Using DomTerm

Up: How to start up and run Kawa

Previous: Running Command Scripts

Next: Exiting Kawa

Installing web page scripts as Servlets

You can compile a Kawa program to a Servlet, and run it in a servlet engine (a Servlet-aware web server). One or more servlets are installed together as a web application. This section includes specific information for the Tomcat and Glassfish web servers.

Creating a web application

A web application is a group of data, servlets, and configuration files to handle a related set of URLs. The servlet specification specifies the directory structure of a web application.

Assume the web application is called myapp, and lives in a directory with the same name. The application normally handles requests for URLs that start with http://example.com/myapp. Most files in the application directory are used to handle requests with corresponding URL. For example, a file myapp/list/help.html would be the response to the request http://example.com/myapp/list/help.html.

The directory WEB-INF is special. It contains configuration files, library code, and other server data.

So to create the myapp application, start with:

mkdir myapp
cd myapp
mkdir WEB-INF WEB-INF/lib WEB-INF/classes

Copy the Kawa jar from the lib direcory. (You can also use a “hard” link, but symbolic links may not work, for security systems.)

cp kawa-home/kawa-2.92_invoke.jar WEB-INF/lib/kawa.jar

If you build Kawa from source, you must specify the --with-servlet configure option.

You should also create the file WEB-INF/web.xml. For now, this is is just a place-holder:

<web-app>
  <display-name>My Application</display-name>
</web-app>

Compiling a web page script to a servlet

Assume for simplicity that the source files are in the WEB-INF/classes directory, and make that the current directory:

cd .../myapp/WEB-INF/classes

Depending on the source language, you compile your script sing the --servlet switch:

kawa --servlet -C hello.scm

or:

kawa --servlet --krl -C hello.krl

or:

kawa --servlet --xquery -C hello.xql

This lets the web-application find the compiled servlets. Finally, you just need to add the new servlet to the WEB-INF/web.xml file:

<web-app>
  <display-name>My Application</display-name>

  <servlet>
    <servlet-name>MyHello</servlet-name>
    <servlet-class>hello</servlet-class>
  </servlet>

  <servlet-mapping>
    <servlet-name>MyHello</servlet-name>
    <url-pattern>/hello</url-pattern>
  </servlet-mapping>
</web-app>

The <servlet> clause says that the servlet named MyHello is implemented by the Java class hello. The <servlet-mapping> clause says that a request URL /hello should be handled by the servlet named MyHello. The URL is relative to the application context path, so the actual URL would be http://example.com/myapp/hello.

Installing a servlet under Tomcat

Apache’s Tomcat is an open-source implementation of the servlet specifications. After you download it, uncompress it in some convenient location, which is commonly referred to as $CATALINA_HOME.

To install your web application, copy/move its directory to be in the $CATALINA_HOME/webapps directory. Thus for the example above you would have a $CATALINA_HOME/webapps/myapp directory.

To start or stop Tomcat use the scripts in $CATALINA_HOME/bin. For example to start Tomcat on a GNU/Linux system run $CATALINA_HOME/bin/startup.sh. This will start a web server that listens on the default port of 8080, so you can browse the above example at http://localhost:8080/myapp/hello.

If you’re running Fedora GNU/Linux, you can use the tomcat6 package:

# yum install tomcat6
# export CATALINA_HOME=/usr/share/tomcat6

You can the manage Tomcat like other system services. You can install webapps under $CATALINA_HOME/webapps.

Installing a servlet under Glassfish

Glassfish from Oracle/Sun is a open-source “application server” that implements Java EE 6, including the 3.0 servlet specification. After you download it, uncompress it in some convenient location. This location is called as-install-parent in the Quick Start Guide. The commands you will use is most in as-install/bin, where as-install is as-install/glassfish.

To start the server, do:

as-install/bin/startserv

or under under Windows:

as-install\bin\startserv.bat

The default post to listen to is 8080; you can the port (and lots of other properties) using the adminstration console at port 4848.

A web application does not need to be any particular location, instead you just install it with this command:

as-install/bin/adadmin deploy appdir

where appdir is the application directory - myapp in the example. (Use asadmin.bat under Windows.)

Servlet-specific script functions

The following functions only work within a servlet container. To use these functions, first do:

(require 'servlets)

You can conditionalize your code to check at compile-time for servlets, like this:

(cond-expand
 (in-servlet
   (require 'servlets)
   (format "[servlet-context: ~s]" (current-servlet-context)))
 (else
   "[Not in a servlet]"))

For a run-time check you can test if (current-servlet) is non-#!null.

Procedure: current-servlet

When called from a Kawa servlet handler, returns the actual javax.servlet.http.HttpServlet instance. Returns #!null if the current context is not that of KawaServlet. (Hence this function also returns #!null if you compile a servlet “by hand” rather that using the --servet option.)

Procedure: current-servlet-context

Returns the context of the currently executing servlet, as an instance of javax.servlet.ServletContext.

Procedure: current-servlet-config

Returns the ServletConfig of the currently executing servlet.

Procedure: get-request

Return the current servlet request, as an instance of javax.servlet.http.HttpServletRequest.

Procedure: get-response

Return the current servlet response, as an instance of javax.servlet.http.HttpServletResponse.

Procedure: request-servlet-path

Get the servlet path of the current request. Similar to request-script-path, but not always the same, depending on configuration, and does not end with a "/".

Procedure: request-path-info

Get the path info of the current request. Corresponds to the CGI variable PATH_INFO.

Procedure: servlet-context-realpath [path]

Returns the file path of the current servlet’s "Web application".

Creating a web application
Compiling a web page script to a servlet
Installing a servlet under Tomcat
Installing a servlet under Glassfish
Servlet-specific script functions

Up: Working with XML and HTML

Previous: Self-configuring web page scripts

Next: Installing Kawa programs as CGI scripts

Functions

To declare a new function use define, which has the following form:

(define (function-name parameter-names) body)

This creates a new function named function-name, which takes parameter-names as parameters. When the function is called, the parameter-names are initialized with the actual arguments. Then body is evaluated, and its value becomes the result of the call.

For example, in the factorial function we looked at recently, the function-name is factorial, and the parameter-names is x:

(define (factorial x)
  (if (< x 1) 1
  (* x (factorial (- x 1)))))

Anonymous functions

An anonymous function is simply a function which does not have a name. We define an anonymous function using a lambda expression, which has the following form:

(lambda (parameter-names) body)

The lambda expression has the parameter-names and body of a function, but it has no name. What is the point of this?

An important example is creating a function to act on a list, perhaps using map. The map function takes two parameters: the first is a function which takes a value and returns a value; the second is a list. Here, we want to double every number in the list.

The usual way of doing this is to create a named function, called double, and then apply it to a list:

#|kawa:1|# (define (double x)
#|.....2|#    (* 2 x))
#|kawa:3|# (map double (list 1 2 3 4 5))
(2 4 6 8 10)

Instead, anonymous functions make it easy to create a function to work on a list, without having to define it in advance:

#|kawa:4|# (map (lambda (x) (* 2 x)) (list 1 2 3 4 5))
(2 4 6 8 10)
#|kawa:5|# (define y 3)
#|kawa:6|# (map (lambda (x) (* x y)) (list 1 2 3 4 5))
(3 6 9 12 15)

The first example shows the double example rewritten as an anonymous function. The second example shows how the anonymous function can be changed to fit the place in which it is used: here, the value of y determines the value by which the list values are multiplied.

Notice that we can name our anonymous functions, in just the same way we name any value in Kawa, using define:

(define double
   (lambda (n)
       (* 2 n)))

although more frequently we use the short-hand for defining functions, which we have already met:

(define (double n)
  (* 2 n))

Anonymous functions are “first-class values” in Kawa, and can be passed to other functions as arguments (like we did with map), and they can even be created and returned by functions as results.

Optional, rest and keyword parameters

You can declare a function that takes optional arguments, or a variable number of arguments. You can also use keyword parameters.

The following function illustrates the use of optional arguments. The function identifies an optional argument z: if the function is called with 3 arguments, z will be bound to the third value, otherwise it will be #f.

(define (addup x y #!optional z)
  (if z
    (+ x y z)
    (+ x y)))

The following examples show addup applied to 2, 3 and invalid arguments. It is an error to pass just one argument or more than three: x and y are compulsory, but z is optional.

#|kawa:12|# (addup 1 2)
3
#|kawa:13|# (addup 1 2 3)
6
#|kawa:14|# (addup 1)
/dev/stdin:14:1: call to 'addup' has too few arguments (1; min=2, max=3)
#|kawa:15|# (addup 1 2 3 4)
/dev/stdin:15:1: call to 'addup' has too many arguments (4; min=2, max=3)

In this example, a better way to define the function would be to include a default value for z, for when its value is not given by the caller. This is done as follows, with the same behavior as above:

(define (addup x y #!optional (z 0))
  (+ x y z))

You can include as many optional parameters as you wish, after the #!optional.

Rest arguments are an alternative way to pass an undefined number of arguments to a function. Here is addup written with rest arguments, notice the variable name after the . (dot):

(define (addup x y . args)
  (+ x y (apply + args)))

The args are simply a list of all remaining values. The following now all work, as the function only requires a minimum of two numbers:

#|kawa:4|# (addup 1 2)
3
#|kawa:5|# (addup 1 2 3)
6
#|kawa:6|# (addup 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8)
36

An alternative way to identify the rest args is with #!rest:

(define (addup x y #!rest args)
  (+ x y (apply + args)))

Finally, it can be useful to identify parameters by name and, for this, Kawa provides keyword arguments. Consider the following function:

(define (vector-3d #!key x y z)
  (make-vector x y z))
#|kawa:40|# (vector-3d #:x 2 #:z 3 #:y 4)
#(2 4 3)

vector-3d is defined with three keyword arguments: x, y, and z. When the function is called, we identify the name for each value by writing #: at the start of the name. This allows us to write the arguments in any order. Keyword parameters can also be given default values, as with optional parameters. Keyword parameters with no default value, and no value in the caller, will get the value #f.

In the caller, keywords are symbols with #: at the front (or : at the end): read more here.

All these extended types of arguments are available both for “named” and for “anonymous” functions. Optional, rest and keyword arguments can be mixed together, along with the usual arguments. For details read more here.

Up: Kawa Scheme Tutorial

Previous: Numbers

Next: Variables

Introduction

You’ve heard about all the hot scripting languages – you might even be tired of hearing about them. But Kawa offers you something different than the scripting-language du-jour can. You may be interested in one that runs on the Java virtual machine, either because you have to interact with other Java tools, or because you like having access to all the Java packages out there. Or maybe you don’t care about Java, but you care about performance. If so, let me tell you about Kawa, which is actually one of the very oldest language implementations running on the Java Virtual Machine, dating back to 1996.

The Kawa language is a dialect/implementation of the Scheme language. (The Kawa project also supports other languages, including XQuery and Emacs Lisp, as well as tools for implementing mew programming languages, but we won’t cover that in this tutorial.)

Scheme is an established language with many implementations, a standard specification (the traditional R5RS, R6RS which was ratified in 2007, and R7RS which was ratified in 2013), and is used by universities for both teaching and research. Scheme also has a reputation for being difficult to learn, with a weird parenthesis-heavy syntax, and hard-to-understand concepts like continuations. Luckily, you don’t need to understand continuations! (Kawa doesn’t fully implement them anyway.)

The following assumes that Kawa is already installed on your computer; if not see these installation instructions. Running the kawa command in interactive mode is a good way start learning Kawa:

$ kawa
#|kawa:1|# 

If you don’t have kawa but you have a Kawa “jar” and you have Java installed you can instead do:

$ java -jar kawa-version-number.jar
#|kawa:1|# 

The prompt string has the form of a Scheme comment, to make it easier to cut-and-paste. Kawa is expecting you type in an expression or command, which it will evaluate, and then print out the result. For example, a quoted string is a simple expression that evaluates to a string value, which will print as itself, before printing the next prompt:

#|kawa:1|# "Hello, world!"
Hello, world!
#|kawa:2|# 

The most noticable difference from most other programming languages is that Scheme uses “prefix” notation for function calls. For example Kawa has a function max which returns the largest value of the arguments. Instead of max(5, 7, 3) you write (max 5 7 3):

(max 5 7 3) ⇒ 7

(We use the ⇒ symbol above to indicate that the expression (max 5 7 3) evaluates to the value 7.)

The prefix notation may feel a bit weird, but you quickly get used to it, and it has some advantages. One is consistency: What are special infix operators in most languages are just regular functions in Scheme. For example, addition is just a regular function call, and + is just a regular function name:

(+ 2.5 1.2) ⇒ 3.7

The same prefix notation is used for special operations like assignments:

#|kawa:1|# (set! sqrt-of-2 (sqrt 2))
#|kawa:2|# sqrt-of-2
1.4142135623730951

Up: Kawa Scheme Tutorial

Next: Booleans

Numbers

Exact integers and fractions

Kawa has the usual syntax for decimal integers. Addition, subtraction, and multiplication are written using the usual +, -, and *, but these are all prefix functions that take a variable number of arguments:

(+ 1 2 3) ⇒ 6
(- 10 3 4) ⇒ (- (- 10 3) 4)  ⇒ 3
(* 2 -6)  ⇒ -12

Kawa has arbitrary-precision integers.

Let us implement the factorial function. Type in the following (we’ll look at the syntax shortly):

#|kawa:1|# (define (factorial x)
#|(---:2|#   (if (< x 1) 1
#|(---:3|#     (* x (factorial (- x 1)))))

(The prompt changes to indicate a continuation line.) This binds the name factorial to a new function, with formal parameter x. This new function is immediately compiled to Java bytecodes, and later a JIT compiler may compile it to native code.

A few tests:

#|kawa:4|# (list (factorial 3) (factorial 4))
(6 24)
#|kawa:5|# (factorial 30)
265252859812191058636308480000000

Floating-point real numbers

Given what was said above about being able to add, subtract and multiply integers, the following may be unexpected:

#|kawa:1|# (/ 2 3)
2/3
#|kawa:2|# (+ (/ 1 3) (/ 2 3))
1

In many languages, dividing two integers, as 2/3, would result in 0. At best, the result would be a floating point number, similar to 0.666667. Instead, Kawa has a rational number type, which holds the results of divisions exactly, as a proper fraction. Hence, adding one third to two thirds will always result in exactly one.

Floating-point real numbers are known in Kawa as inexact numbers, as they cannot be stored exactly. Consider:

#|kawa:3|# (exact? 2/3)
#t
#|kawa:4|# (exact? 0.33333333)
#f
#|kawa:5|# (exact->inexact 2/3)
0.6666666666666666

The first two examples check numbers for being exact?; there is a corresponding inexact? test. The last shows how an exact number can be converted to an inexact form.

Numbers are converted between exact and inexact versions when required within operations or procedures:

#|kawa:6|# (+ 0.33333333 2/3)
0.9999999966666666
#|kawa:7|# (inexact? (+ 0.33333333 2/3))
#t
#|kawa:8|# (sin 2/3)
0.618369803069737

Complex numbers

A complex number is made from two parts: a real part and an imaginary part. They are written 2+3i. A complex number can be manipulated just like other numbers:

#|kawa:9|# (+ 2+3i 5+2i)
7+5i
#|kawa:10|# (* 2+3i 4-3i)
17+6i
#|kawa:11|# (integer? (+ 2+3i -3i))
#t

Notice how in the last example the result is an integer, which Kawa recognises.

Kawa also includes quaternion numbers.

Units and dimensions

In many applications, numbers have a unit. For example, 5 might be a number of dollar bills, a weight on a scale, or a speed. Kawa enables us to represent numbers as quantities: numbers along with their unit. For example, with weight, we might measure weight in pounds and ounces, where an ounce is 1/16 of a pound.

Using Kawa, we can define units for our weight measurements, and specify the units along with numbers:

#|kawa:12|# (define-base-unit pound "Weight")
#|kawa:13|# (define-unit ounce 0.0625pound)
#|kawa:14|# 3pound
3.0pound
#|kawa:15|# (+ 1pound 5ounce)
1.3125pound

In this example we define a base unit, the pound, and a unit based on it, the ounce, which is valued at 0.0625 pounds (one sixteenth). Numbers can then be written along with their unit (making them quantities). Arithmetic is possible with quantities, as shown in the last line, and Kawa will do the smart thing when combining units. In this case, 1 pound and 5 ounces is combined to make 1.3125 pounds.

Up: Kawa Scheme Tutorial

Previous: Booleans

Next: Functions

Types

A type is a set of values, plus an associated set of operations valid on those values. Types are useful for catching errors ("type-checking"), documenting the programmer’s intent, and to help the compiler generate better code. Types in some languages (such as C) appear in programs, but do not exist at run-time. In such languages, all type-checking is done at compile-time. Other languages (such as standard Scheme) do not have types as such, but they have predicates, which allow you to check if a value is a member of certain sets; also, the primitive functions will check at run-time if the arguments are members of the allowed sets. Other languages, including Java and Common Lisp, provide a combination: Types may be used as specifiers to guide the compiler, but also exist as actual run-time values. In Java, for each class, there is a corresponding java.lang.Class run-time object, as well as an associated type (the set of values of that class, plus its sub-classes, plus null).

Kawa, like Java, has first-class types, that is types exist as objects you can pass around at run-time. For each Java type, there is a corresponding Kawa type (but not necessarily vice versa). It would be nice if we could represent run-time type values using java.lang.Class objects, but unfortunately that does not work very well. One reason is that we need to be able to refer to types and classes that do not exist yet, because we are in the processing of compiling them. Another reason is that we want to be able to distinguish between different types that are implemented using the same Java class.

Various Kawa constructs require or allow a type to be specified. Those specifications consist of type expressions, and a type expression is evaluated to yield a type value. The current Kawa compiler is rather simple-minded, and in many places only allows simple types that the compiler can evaluate at compile-time. More specifically, it only allows simple type names that map to primitive Java types or Java classes.

type ::= expression
opt-type-specifier ::= [:: type]

Standard Types
Parameterized Types
Type tests and conversions

Up: Part . Reference Documentation

Previous: Input, output, and file handling

Next: Object, Classes and Modules

Acknowledgements and thanks

The author and project leader of Kawa is Per Bothner <per@bothner.com>.

Kawa is a re-write of Kawa 0.2, which was a Scheme interpreter written by R. Alexander Milowski <alex@milowski.com>.

Thanks to Cygnus Solutions (now part of Red Hat) for sponsoring the initial development of Kawa, and then transferring their ownership interest to Per.

Financial support

Ean Schuessler and Brainfood provided financial support and encouragement.

Thanks to Chris Dean, Dean Ferreyra, and others at Merced Systems for financial support and other contributions.

Google through their Summer of Code project sponsored Charles Turner during Summer 2011 and 2012, and sponsored Andrea Bernardini Summer 2014.

Thomas Kirk and AT&T provided financial support, and useful bug reports.

Various contributions

Jakub Jankiewicz contributed the Kawa logo.

Helmut Eller provided SLIME support, syntaxutils.scm, and many bug reports.

Daniel Bonniot for multiple small improvements to gnu.bytecode and gnu.expr.

Jamison Hope for multiple contributions, including quaternion support, the SRFI-14 implementation, Ant improvements, and Google Summer of Code mentoring.

Jim White for Ant support and other improvements.

Bruce R. Lewis implemented KRL and made other contributions.

Geoff Berry: Handle Exceptions attribute. Other improvements.

Shad Gregory improved JEmacs.

Al Petrofsky improved gnu.math printing and added some IntNum methods.

Marco Vezzoli: SRFI-1 tailoring for Kawa.

Albert Ting - old GuiConsole code.

Christian Surlykke ported JEmacs to use SWT.

Geoff Berry for various gnu.bytecode improvements.

Ivelin Ivanov and Tom Reilly for servlet support.

Anthony Green for Fedora packaging.

Charles Turner for pretty-printer improvements, improvements in the Common Lips support, and other changes.

Andrea Bernardini optimized the implementation of case.

Julien Rousseau and Marius Kjeldahl contributed to Android support.

Peter Lane for many documentation improvements.

Small fixes and improvements

Patrick Barta; Joseph Bowbeer; Dominique Boucher; Alexander Bunkenburg; Harold Carr; Emmanuel Castro; Álvaro Castro-Castilla; Heather Downs; Francisco Vides Fernández; Nic Ferrier; Oliver Flasch; Weiqi Gao; Luke Gorrie; Mario Domenech Goulart; Zvi Har’E; Jeff Haynes; Ethan Herdrick; Joerg-Cyril Hoehle; Elliott Hughes; Mike Kenne; Brian Jones; Gerardo Jorvilleur; Simon Josefsson (JEmacs menu); Thomas Kirk; Jay Krell; Edouard Parmelan; Walter C. Pelissero; Rafael Jesus Alcantara Perez; Lynn Quam; Marcus Otto; Terje Pedersen (some XQuery functions); Matthias Radestock; Ola Rinta-Koski; Andreas Schlapbach; Robert D. Skeels; Benny Tsai; Vladimir Tsichevski; Matthieu Vachon; Phil Walker; Knut Wannheden; Chris Wegrzyn.

Bug reports and test cases

Seth Alves; Khairul Azhar; Bob Bane; Hans Boehm; Adrián Medraño Calvo; Brian D. Carlstrom; Luis Casillas; Sudarshan S Chawathe; Ken Dickey (format tests); Helge Dietert; Allan Erskine; Marc Feeley (polytype.scm); Margus Freudenthal; Weiqi Gao; Andrea Girotto; Norman Hard; Gerardo Horvilleur; Yaroslav Kavenchuk; Felix S Klock II; Francois Leygues; Mirko Luedde; Leonardo Valeri Manera; Kjetil S. Matheussen; Alex Mitchell; Alex Moiseenko Edouard Parmelan; Walter C. Pelissero; Stephen L. Peters; François Pinard; Bill Robinson; Dan Stanger (Eaton Vance); Hallvard Traetteberg; Taylor Venable; Alessandro Vernet; Tony White John Whittaker; Robert Yokota.

Code ported from other packages

Kawa includes Free Software originally written for other purposes, but incorporated into Kawa, perhaps with some porting. A partial list:

Dorai Sitaram wrote pregexp.

The rationalize algorithm is by Alan Bawden and Marc Feeley.

Lars T Hansen wrote SRFI-11 (let-values, let*-values macros).

Olin Shivers wrote the SRFI-1 list-processing library, and the SRFI-13 reference impementation.

John David Stone wrote SRFI-8 (receive macro)

Jussi Piitulainen wrote the SRFI-25 specification and tests.

Richard Kelsey and Michael Sperber wrote SRFI-34.

Anthony Carrico wrote the SRFI-37 reference implementation.

Panu Kalliokoski wrote the SRFI-69 reference implementation.

Donovan Kolbly wrote the srfi-64 “meta” testsuite. Alex Shinn improved SRFI-64 portability.

Philip L. Bewig wrote the SRFI-41 (streams) specification and reference implementation.

Simon Tatham wrote listsort.

Aubrey Jaffer wrote much of SLIB, some of which has been imported into gnu.kawa.slib. He also wrote some tests we’re using.

Up: The Kawa Community

Previous: General Kawa email and discussion

Next: Technical Support for Kawa